<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Quakers unmasked their double-dealing and false-heartedness discovered by collections taken out of their own writings, which were communicated to G. Fox, G. Whitehead, and others of their preachers and leaders : wherein may be seen some of their contradictions thereupon by another hand : also, one of the forms of their oaths, used amongst themselves, with their definition of an oath : likewise a letter and paper formerly sent to the abovesaid G.F. : whereunto are annexed some remarks, &amp;c. : also what an oath is : in a letter to E.S. ...</title>
            <author>Pennyman, John, 1628-1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31105</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11779325</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11779325</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48969</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54263)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48969)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1491:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Quakers unmasked their double-dealing and false-heartedness discovered by collections taken out of their own writings, which were communicated to G. Fox, G. Whitehead, and others of their preachers and leaders : wherein may be seen some of their contradictions thereupon by another hand : also, one of the forms of their oaths, used amongst themselves, with their definition of an oath : likewise a letter and paper formerly sent to the abovesaid G.F. : whereunto are annexed some remarks, &amp;c. : also what an oath is : in a letter to E.S. ...</title>
                  <author>Pennyman, John, 1628-1706.</author>
                  <author>A. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, 28, 7 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Gwillim ... and R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints to Pennyman.</note>
                  <note>"The author ... to reader" signed: J.P. [i.e. John Pennyman]</note>
                  <note>Page 1-23 printed in parallel columns, the first, "Geo. Fox's judgment concerning kingly government ... before the king was restored",  the other, "G. Fox his judgment concerning kingly government, since the king was restored."</note>
                  <note>"Some remarks upon a book entitled Christ's lambs defended against Satan's rage, &amp;c. : being the Quakers answer to The Quakers unmask'd, &amp;c. : in a letter to E.S. ..." signed: A.C. p. 1-6 at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</term>
               <term>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48969:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:48969:1"/>
            <p>THE Quakers Unmask'd; Their <hi>Double-dealing</hi> and <hi>Falſe-heartedneſs</hi> Diſcovered; BY <hi>Collections</hi> taken out of their own <hi>Writings,</hi> which were Communicated to <hi>G. Fox, G. Whitehead,</hi> and others of their <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Leaders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN May be ſeen ſome of their <hi>Contradictions, Confuſions,</hi> and <hi>Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing:</hi> With ſome <hi>Obſervations</hi> thereupon by another Hand.</p>
            <p>ALSO, One of the <hi>Forms</hi> of their <hi>Oaths,</hi> uſed amongſt themſelves, with their Definition of an <hi>Oath:</hi> Likewiſe a Letter and Paper formerly ſent to the aboveſaid <hi>G. F.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto are annexed ſome Remarks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Alſo what an <hi>Oath</hi> is. In a Letter to <hi>E. S.</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> LICENSED, <hi>June</hi> 19. 1691</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The <hi>Leaders</hi> the <hi>Leaders</hi> of this</hi> People <hi>have cauſed them to Err, becauſe they received not the</hi> Truth <hi>in the</hi> Love <hi>of it; Therefore are they given up to <hi>Strong Deluſions,</hi> to believe (and to tell) <hi>Lies.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Day <hi>is come, and now is, that the Hidden Things of</hi> Eſau<hi>'s</hi> Nature, <hi>are to be, and muſt be brought to Light.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>O thou <hi>Sword</hi> of the</hi> LORD, <hi>How long will it be e'er thou be quiet? Put up thy ſelf into thy Scabbard, reſt and be ſtill. How can it be quiet, ſeeing the</hi> LORD <hi>hath given it a Charge?</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Gwillim</hi> over againſt the <hi>Great James</hi> in <hi>Biſhops-gate-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>R. Baldwin</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48969:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48969:2"/>
            <head>The Author of the following Collections to the READER.</head>
            <p>IT can hardly be credited by any, the care and fear I have had concerning the ſaid Collections, leſt they ſhould have become publick in the laſt two Reigns, which I would not they ſhould for the Treaſures of this World. <hi>This is a faithful and true ſaying, whether it can be believed or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now Liberty of Conſcience being establiſhed by Law, I gave Ten of 'em, <hi>[i. e. <hi>The Quakers Vnmask'd,]</hi>
               </hi> to be ſhown or ſold to any ſober Perſon; unto which ſome of the Leaders of that People have lately put forth an Anſwer; and finding they are ſo far from acknowledging any thing to be amiſs in their ſaid Writings, that they endeavour either to cover, excuſe, or juſtifie them, which hath neceſſitated me to cauſe them to be reprinted in <hi>Quarto,</hi> that whoever have ſeen their Anſwer, may, if they pleaſe, compare it with this.</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding I ſent them the ſaid Book privately in writing, in the year <hi>77.</hi> (hoping thereby to have prevented their farther expoſing others;) yet, about a year after, I met with a Book of theirs, intitled, <hi>
                  <hi>The Way caſt up,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> and therein ſeveral paſſages againſt the Presbyterians, accuſing them of <hi>
                  <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, Seditions, and Fighting Principles.</hi> p. 23, 52, 53, 54.</hi> And in the year <hi>81.</hi> they put forth another Book, calling it, <hi>
                  <hi>Peaceable Advice to the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> and therein, <hi>p. 1.</hi> accuſed them again with the ſame Principles; which being Printed at ſuch a juncture, when the Popiſh Plot was endeavoured to be ſtifled, and turned upon the Proteſtants, cauſed a great grief not only to my ſelf, but to many others; ſome of whom writ to the Quaker's Bookſeller, <hi>deſiring they might be ſtopt conſidering the ſeaſon,</hi> &amp;c. But they not prevailing in, their Requeſt, I bought many of 'em, and went to ſeveral of their Meetings, where I ſpake theſe Words, <hi>viz. I met with one of your Books againſt the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, and as a Witneſs againſt that <hi>Hypocritical, Deceitful, Daubing, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing Spirit</hi> that writ it, and the Publiſhers of it, I am made to tear it in pieces before you.</hi> Which having done, they threatned to have me called in Queſtion for it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſay, conſidering theſe things, and that what I had writ to them in private did not hinder them from this continued exclaiming againſt others about theſe matters. It was thought meet to have <hi>66</hi> of <hi>The Quakers Vnmask'd,</hi> privately printed in <hi>Folio;</hi> which were chiefly intended to be given to ſome of the ſaid People, ſo that it is plain my purpoſe and intention therein was only to prevent, if poſſible, their doing any more ſuch things for the future; but not in the least to expoſe them to the then Governours, who I feared would have been but too ſevere, and too much exaſperated againſt them for it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48969:3"/>
And though I have been made thus to adviſe and caution them from their run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into theſe and many other Evils, (which they have run themſelves into:) Yet alas! they have ſlighted, ſcorned, and rejected every thing I propoſed, that might any way have conduced to their preſent Happineſs, and everlaſting Good; which being my chiefeſt end, aim, and endeavour; whether they will yet hear, or forbear, I am clear, and have that Reward with, and in me, which no Man non Men can give, or take from me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publisher_to_the_reader">
            <head>This following was writ by the Perſon that cauſed the 66 Books aforeſaid, in <hi>Folio,</hi> to be printed.</head>
            <head type="sub">The <hi>Publiſher</hi> to the truly <hi>Chriſtian Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE following <hi>Tract</hi> Providentially coming to my Hand, and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to Read and Conſider it, I ſpent ſome Hours therein, to my no ſmall Conſternation, upon a double account. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Land of my Nativity was not long ere this, an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> being ſo generally <hi>Apoſtatized</hi> from the <hi>Truth,</hi> and become a ſecond <hi>
                  <hi>Sodom.</hi> Secondly,</hi> To conſider, That the <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Forwardeſt LEADERS</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> who (while Faithful) were begirt with the Power and Strength of the Almighty GOD of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and brought to their <hi>PISGAH-SIGHT,</hi> ſhould turn again to their <hi>Onions and Garlick,</hi> throwing by the ROYAL LAW of LIBERTY, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſpouſe <hi>Egyptian Bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay to theſe things! Oh that the Souls of all that are yet Faithful, and have according to their meaſure, been given up to the Guidance of the Spirit, would Cry mightily unto the GOD of their Salvation; That every one concern'd in the following HURRICANE, (which they have been formerly warned off, in Love and Meekneſs, about four years and half ſince,) may remember from whence they are Fallen, repent and do their Firſt Works, (which is the principal End of the Printing hereof,) that ſo the <hi>Still Voice,</hi> may be Reſtored in all our Habitations, That all Weapons of War may be turned into Plow-ſhares and Pruning-hooks, and every One confeſs, The LORD is GOD, who only muſt and will be Exalted. Amen, amen, ſaith the Soul of thy Friend,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. G.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note.</hi> Where any Words are added that were not in the Manuſcript, or in that Printed, they are put in <hi>Italick</hi> between theſe Marks, []. excepting 5 ſhort Sentences in Black Letter, <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4, 5, which were left out for brevity but are now put in only to ſhew they do not in the leaſt vary the ſenſe, as the Quakers alleadge in their Anſwer, no more than any other paſſage they have mentioned therein does.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48969:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader. The three following Letters were writ to Mr. <hi>J. O.</hi> The firſt was Printed the other not.</head>
            <div n="1" type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>First Letter to Mr.</hi> J. O. <hi>ſent with the following Book then not printed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Having been ill and weak in Body near upon a Month; it put me upon a deep ſearch and examination, concerning the Cauſe thereof; and finding my ſelf clear in HIS ſight who juſtifies in ſecret, I matter not who condemns: And now being a little raiſed up, and reſtored for a ſeaſon from the Grave, I have further conſidered what my Work and Service is in my Generation; and do find a neceſſity laid upon me to be Inſtrumental for the diſcovering, unmasking, and manifeſting your <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Leaders,</hi> who have long exerciſed <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Cruelty</hi> over the Souls of the Righteous, and who (by their Threats and Flatteries) have cauſed many innocent Men and Women to bend and bow under them, contrary to their own Conſciences; for which they muſt certainly give an account; and ſo muſt you that are the Upholders of them.</p>
               <p>The Book herewith ſent, I deſire may be ſhew'd to the Perſons to whom it is directed; it will concern you to conſult and conſider how the <hi>Truth</hi> (which you have ſo long talked of in Words) may be Cleared, and the <hi>Hypocrite <hi>and</hi> Deceiver</hi> made to bear his own Burden, of which if I may be aſſured, my End in ſending it will be fully anſwered, and it will be a ſufficient Recompenſe for all the Care and Pains I have taken therein, and ſhall endeavour to prevent and ſtop its farther Publication. But if in the Pride of your Hearts, you ſhall kick and ſpurn againſt it, reject and deſpiſe my Counſel herein given you; then know that your Iniquities will be upon your own Heads, when I ſhall be clear in my Conſcience concerning you.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>I am a Lover of TRUTH and RIGHTEOUSNESS, In whomſoever:</item>
                  <item>But an utter Enemy to <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> In whomſoever:</item>
               </list>
               <p>I got one to Copy out the Book fair over, but am not ſo well to ſee it carefully Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined; therefore if you find any miſtake in the Quotations, let me know it in two or three Weeks time, and it ſhall be rectiſied before it go farther.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>10. <hi>Oct.</hi> 1677.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>J. P.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="letter">
               <head>Second Letter to Mr. <hi>O.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>'TIS now near 6 Weeks ſince I ſent you the <hi>
                     <hi>Quakers Vnmask'd,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> which I deſired might be imparted to <hi>G.F. G.W.</hi> &amp;c. from whom (or ſome of you) I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected an Anſwer; but not hearing from any of you concerning it, I take it for granted you are ſatisfied I have not wronged you in the Quotations, and therefore it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned by this Bearer.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>20. <hi>Nov.</hi> 77.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>J. P.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="letter">
               <head>But inſtead of returning the ſaid Book, as I deſired, he ſent me part of a Letter writ to him by <hi>G. W.</hi> which occaſioned me to write this following Anſwer.</head>
               <head type="sub">Third Letter to Mr. <hi>O.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Perceive by a Letter directed to you, there is an Anſwer to the Book I ſent you; but it ſeems I muſt not ſee it before it is Printed, as you have mine; neither may I ſee the Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood, <hi>which in divers particulars, as to matter of Fact, (they ſay) I am guilty of,</hi> that if any ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:48969:4"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be, it might be amended; but they act herein more like Politicians, than either Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Chriſt, or juſt Men; and deal by me in <hi>this,</hi> much as you did with <hi>J. Whitehouſe</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom your Meeting drew up a Charge, yet would not give him a Copy thereof; but when it came to be your own Caſe, that ſome of your Friends were accuſed for Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cariages, then you could ſay, <hi>It was below the Juſtice of all Nations not to give a Copy of the Charge.</hi> Thus you can ſay, and unſay, do and not do, as ſuits beſt (not with Truth, but) with your own Self-ends and Intereſts. If Truth and Plain-heartedneſs were with you, why ſhould not I ſee your Anſwer, <hi>[before publication]</hi> as well as you ſee my Book? But Guilt and Deceit makes ſhy. Call a Council of your wiſeſt Men, to conſult what you had beſt to do in this matter, in which your chiefeſt Preachers are greatly guilty of abominable Wickedneſs in the ſight of GOD and juſt Men: And if a neceſſity be upon me <hi>[as now it is]</hi> to publiſh mine, (if you will not doe the thing that is right to prevent it,) to bring out yours; then ſay the wiſe are taken in their own Craftineſs, <hi>[which is now fulfilled].</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot but wonder at their ſaying, that <hi>'tis a violation of the Act of Indemnity</hi> what I have done in this buſineſs, when they (as well as my ſelf) know that all things of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are thereby pardoned, as to Men: But their tranſgreſſion is of a deeper dye, than the breach of Man's Law only; for they have pretended to be Miniſters and Meſſengers of the moſt <hi>High GOD,</hi> and what they writ was by His Authority, when really and truly it was but the Imaginations and Inventions of their own deceived Hearts; to manifeſt which, and to undeceive the Minds of the Simple, who are beguiled (as my ſelf once was) by their ſpecious and high Pretences, I have taken the pains to write out ſome of their Meſſages, which do apparently ſhew they are but pretenders only; and have made uſe of the Name of the LORD to cover and carry on their own deſigns; and when it ſuits not with their Intereſts, then would they have ſuch Meſſages hid, and not brought to light.</p>
               <p>Are theſe the Embaſſadors of the moſt <hi>High,</hi> who for any worldly ends, or carnal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, would have His Commands and Requirings ſtifled, which they ſaid they gave forth in His <hi>Name?</hi> Surely their Hypocriſie and Deceit appears, and will yet appear more and more.</p>
               <p>Behold, you great <hi>Goliahs!</hi> your ſtrength is in an Arm of Fleſh, but mine is only in the Living GOD, before whom all your deceitful Covers are manifeſt, which will ſtand you in little ſtead in the Day of Diſtreſs, that is coming upon you; for <hi>He</hi> will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly plead with you for all your Abominations: You are full of deſigns to keep up your Eſteem amonſt the People; but the LORD (by whoſe Power I am raiſed up againſt you) will bring you low, and utter diſgrace will come upon you, becauſe you have not ſought <hi>His</hi> Glory ſo much as your own; and if thou continues and joyns with them in their Sins, thou muſt not expect to eſcape their Judgments.</p>
               <p>It is certainly ſo, that I have been your trueſt Friend, (though accounted your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,) and have in all Faithfulneſs diſcharged my Conſcience towards you; and what I am to do farther in this matter, it concerns me diligently to wait upon <hi>HIM</hi> who gives Wiſdom to the Simple, to confound the Wiſdom of the Wiſe; and I am aſſured that Simplicity and Innocency will ſtand, when all the cunning Contrivances of Men ſhall fall. I am</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>The Friend in Truth, without Flattery,</hi> J. P.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>Dec.</hi> 19. 77.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>I deſire <hi>G. F. G. Whitehead</hi> may ſee this, or any you ſee meet.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:48969:4"/>
            <head>The PREFACE</head>
            <p>WHen I have conſidered how the <hi>Quakers,</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> G.F. G. Whitehead, <hi>and the reſt of that Temporizing, Imperious, <hi>Lording Party,</hi>
               </hi>) have Writ and Printed againſt the <hi>Presbyterians, Independents,</hi> and others for being Engaged in the late Wars, and what opprobrious, villifying, and reproachful Terms they have given them for the ſame, it hath exceedingly amazed and aſtoniſhed me, that they who were ſo Great Juſtifiers and Encouragers, not only of what had been done in the late Wars, but alſo did incite and encourage thoſe that were therein engaged, not to leave off until they had ſet up their STANDARD at the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> as may be ſeen in their own Writings here following: And yet for them to upbraid others with that which themſelves for many years were ſo deeply concerned and engaged in, is ſuch a piece of <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> as can hardly be parallel'd by any ſort of People profeſſing Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>This, this their <hi>Baſeneſs,</hi> I have in ſecret acquainted them withal, but no <hi>Ear</hi> or <hi>Heed</hi> would they give to what I ſaid, but ſtill went on in their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed manner to Defame ſuch as had not been more engaged, if ſo much as themſelves, in the late Wars; yea, and that in the moſt revengeful and higheſt aggravating Terms, that 'twas poſſible for their <hi>Penn</hi> to expreſs; wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thoſe Words to the <hi>Nonconforming Ministers,</hi> in Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Faldo</hi> (viz.) <hi>But why, poor Nonconformiſts, after all their Preach'd up Battels, Spoils, Plunders, Sacrileges, Decimations,</hi> &amp;c. Again, <hi>They are true Goſpel-miniſters, whoſe Goſpel is Peace on Earth, and Good Will towards Men, and not Garments rolled in the Blood of Kings and Princes, Rulers and People: No Worldly Armies, Battles, Victories, Trophies, Spoils, Sequeſtrations, Decimations, and the like Blood-thirſty and Tyrannical Projects, in which</hi> John Faldo <hi>and his poor Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming Miniſters have had their Hands, almoſt over Head and Ears, till they had well nigh loſt their Ears and their Heads too.</hi> Much more of this Nature may be ſeen towards to the latter end of the leſſer Column of this Book.</p>
            <p>What People, ſetting theſe aſide, could have had the Face and Confidence to have writ ſuch Language as this? Certainly not any; eſpecially when they themſelves had been engaged in the ſame Cauſe and Quarrel with thoſe whom they now ſo much Reproach and Vilifie.</p>
            <p>The Conſideration of theſe things, with their pretending themſelves to be the <hi>Only People</hi> of the LORD, and of their being the <hi>Only Embaſſadors</hi> and <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> with the Diſcharge of my own Conſcience, put me
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48969:5"/>upon gathering theſe their <hi>Writings</hi> together, and having them ſo placed, that thoſe of the meaneſt Capacity may eaſily diſcern and ſee them to be as great <hi>Diſſemblers, Deceivers,</hi> and <hi>Deluders</hi> of the People, as have appear'd in this our Age.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE firſt Column is what they writ before the King came in, the other is what they writ ſince his Return; and as for the Quotations, I have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured faithfulneſs therein, and have cited both <hi>Book</hi> and <hi>Page,</hi> where their Words may be found, but they have left out many Paſſages, and altered ſeveral Words (that ſuited not with their Intereſts and Deſigns) both of <hi>E. B</hi>'s and <hi>F. H</hi>'s in the Re-print of their Works, which thou wilt have notice of as thou readeſt: And where I have abbreviated any of their Writings, or leſt out any of their Words, which were not ſo material to be put in, or too large to inſert, thou wilt find a little ſtroke, thus — but have not in the leaſt either wron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Matter or Senſe thereby, as thou mayeſt ſee if thou peruſe the Books I have quoted.</p>
            <p>But before thou proceedeſt to read farther, I am willing thou ſhouldſt hear the Teſtimony they give of their own Writings, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ther you own the Prophets, Chriſt and the Apoſtles, you will own oue Writings, which are given forth by the ſame Spirit and power.</hi> See <hi>G. F</hi>'s. Anſw. to the <hi>Westmoreland</hi> Petition, p. 30.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You might as well condemn the Scriptures to the Fire as our Queries. Our giving forth Papers or printed Books, it is from the immediate, Eternal Spirit of God. You are now Anſwered from the Mouth of the Lord.</hi> See <hi>G. F.</hi> and <hi>R. H.</hi> Truth's Defence, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 2, 104, 107.</p>
            <p>Now if this their Teſtimony be true, then their Writings are to be had in as great and as venerable eſteem as the Scriptures, or any holy Man's Words are; but if it be otherwiſe, then are they <hi>Lyars</hi> and <hi>falſe Prophets;</hi> and to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided and witneſſed againſt. Let theſe following Collections manifeſt the Truth thereof.</p>
            <p>[<hi>And now the time is come, that as they have laid open the Deceit, Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Hypocriſie of other Profeſſors that went before them; even ſo muſt their Deceit, Wickedneſs, and Hypocriſie be alſo laid open; For the</hi> LORD <hi>whom I no Reſpecter of Perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But who ſhall live when <hi>GOD</hi> doth this!]</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="excerpts">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48969:5"/>
            <head>Geo, Fox's Judgment <hi>CONCERNING KINGLY GOVERNMENT.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Taken out of a Paper of his, written to the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Others,</hi> before the KING was <hi>Reſtored.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO all you that deſire an Earthly King in <hi>England,</hi>— Who profeſs your ſelves to be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> whether <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or <hi>Others.</hi>— Do not the Prieſts, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians, and many of the Rulers cry for an Earthly King?—And is not this the ſame Nature the <hi>Jews</hi> were in? And do not they in <hi>This</hi> Crucifie Jeſus? Are not all theſe Elders Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that will doat ſo much of an Earthly King, <hi>Traytors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt?</hi>—Now Elders, if you ſay, <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid <hi>Honour the King;</hi>—This doth not hold forth that <hi>Peter</hi> bid them ſet up an Earthly King over them, neither do you read—that there were any Earthly Kings ſince the days of the Apoſtles, but among the Apoſtate Chriſtians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— And all theſe <hi>Antichriſts</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> imitated Elders over them all.—Will Chriſt Reign and theſe Kings that have been made? For Chriſt is King alone, and makes his Diſciples Kings,—to Reign upon the Earth.—Theſe are true Chriſtians, and will theſe have any more Kings among them, but Chriſt, who are Redeemed from the Earth and earthly Kings?—I ſay, That is the falſe Church that doth not live upon the Heads of theſe Kings.—Such as have the Prophets, Chriſt, and the Apoſtles Words; the Sheeps Cloathing, but out of the Life and Power that makes ſuch work for an Earthly King.—<hi>Herod</hi> the King was <hi>
                     <hi>Mad</hi> at the Child Jeſus,</hi> and ſought to ſlay all the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in <hi>Bethlehem</hi> of <hi>Judea; There is ehe fruits of Earthly Kings,</hi> and ſuch a King would our falſe Chriſtians and Elders have.</p>
               <p>The Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when they grew, would have Kings like other Nations, that when People were gon from the Lord God, — then they ſet up Kings; and when the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſerved not the Lord God, but went after other gods,—they deſired a King, which the Lord gave them in his Wrath, <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. And in this manner, <hi>Should a King Reign over them, the King ſhall take your Sons and appoint them for his Chariots,</hi> &amp;c.—(this is the fruit of your Kings)—<hi>The King will take your Fields, your Vineyards, your beſt Olive Trees, and give them to his Servants.</hi> (this is the Fruit of your Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>Ignorant and fooliſh People that would have a King
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48969:6"/>and Kings ſince the days of the Apoſtles.</hi>— The People will not hear when all theſe Fruits of theſe Kings are laid down to them.— But ſays Chriſtians and falſe Elders, there ſhall be a King over us, and we alſo will be like other Nations.—So the Chriſtians go out from Chriſt, and ſet up Kings like Heathens, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.11.— You ignorant and fooliſh, that is, looking after Kings, which turns from the Lord.—This is to you Chriſtians, that would have another King.—You may ſee what work there was with the Kings of <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Eſau.</hi>—And when the Children of <hi>Iſſrael</hi> grew into <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Nature, they would have a King.—So the Antichriſts they will have a King,—as other Heatheniſh Nations would have, they will fight elſe, and this is <hi>Eſau</hi>'s Nature.—Now <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> there are Figures in their being Kings. And ſee what work the Kings of the <hi>Midianites</hi> did, and the Children of <hi>Iſral</hi>'s Kings, who ſaid, <hi>Thou art our King, Reign over us, both thou and thy Sons.</hi>—Theſe, like our doating Chriſtians, would have a King.—And read what work the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> made (when they were as Judges in the fear of the Lord) with the Kings of the Earth, the Kings of <hi>Canaan.</hi>—You may ſee what work the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had with <hi>Sihon</hi> King of the <hi>Amorites,</hi> and <hi>Sthon</hi> King of <hi>Heſhbon,</hi> and ſtrange Kings of <hi>Baſhan, Joſh.</hi> 13 —And you may ſee in the 12th. of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> what work he made with the Kings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And how God had hardned the Hearts of the Kings that they might be deſtroyed by them that had no King.—How they over-threw the Kings when they kept faithful to the Lord.— <hi>Joſh.</hi> 11. And how the Lord fought for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and what work <hi>Joſhua</hi> made with the Kings, how he brouhht them out of the <hi>
                     <hi>Care:</hi> A fit place for them</hi> [ſaith <hi>G. Fox</hi>] for all Kings that be made in Mens earthly Wills.—The <hi>Rocks</hi> and <hi>Caves</hi> are their Shelter in time of Diſtreſs.— And you may ſee what Fear and Dread was in all Nations and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, while the <hi>Children of Iſrael</hi> went on in the Name of the Lord; and ſo it will be again, when People go on in the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> what a dread they will be in all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to all Kings, and all ſuch upon the Earth who are Kings and Princes made, but not by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> for all the true redeemed ones, are Kings and Prieſts, that reign upon the Earth, that knew their-<hi>Election</hi> before the World began. You may ſee in the third Chapter of <hi>Deuteronomy:</hi> How the Word of the Lord was fulfilled: How they went over the Kings and ſmote them in the Power of the Lord God:— And as the <hi>Children of Iſrael</hi> dwelt in the Fear of the Lord, the Kings fled before them:—So will they do before all them that live in the Power of God.—The Shout of a King was among the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> while they felt the Lord of Hoſts was among them; <hi>they trod down the Earthly Kings:</hi>—and all theſe <hi>Novice Chriſtians</hi> that are crying up Earthly Kings, and following Kings, and fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Kings of the Earth, are not ſuch as follow the Lamb.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:48969:6"/>
We know that theſe Kings are the <hi>Spiritual Egyptians</hi> got up ſince the days of the Apoſtles. <hi>Joſiah</hi> and ſuch as feared the Lord (in the time of the <hi>Law</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi>) the Lord accepted, which Kings was among the <hi>Jews,</hi> but you never read of any among the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but among the <hi>Apoſtates</hi> ſince the Days of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All which (and much more) you may read in the fore-mentioned Paper of <hi>G. F.</hi> Pag.</hi> 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 18, 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerve.</hi> Here by way of Interrogation he affirms: <hi>That they who cry for an Earthly King, do in this Crucifie Jeſus, and are <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors againſt Chriſt,</hi> and that true Chriſtians will not have any more Kings among them but Chriſt: That the fruit of Earthly Kings, is to be <hi>mad</hi> at the Child Jeſus, as</hi> Herod <hi>was: That they are Ignorant and Fooliſh People that would have a King and Kings, ſince the Days of the Apoſtles: That theſe Kings are the</hi> Spiritual Aegyptians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>
                  <hi>G. Fox</hi> to the Protector and Parliament. <hi>p. 62. 1658.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND now, Oh <hi>Protector!</hi> who haſt taſted of the Power of God,—Take heed thou looſe not thy Power; but keep <hi>Kingſhip</hi> off thy Head, which the World would give thee; and <hi>Earthly Crowns</hi> under thy Feet, leſt with <hi>that</hi> thou cover thy ſelf, <hi>and ſo looſe the Power of God.</hi> ☞ <hi>When the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>went from that of God in them, they would have Kings, as other Nations had, as Tranſgreſſors had, and ſo God gave them one.</hi>] —And ye Powers of the Earth, <hi>take heed of making Earthly Kings,</hi> or looking after Earthly Kings, leſt you hurt and undo your ſelves and others, but mind the Witneſs of God in you, that you may ſee what the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> went from, when they ſet up Kings as other Nations,—Ye <hi>Heathens,</hi>—that ſet up Kings, and know not the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From a Lover of your Souls and Eternal Good, and Eſtabliſhing of Righteouſneſs,</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Again, A Word from the Lord, &amp;c. <hi>p. 15, 1654.</hi> (he ſaith)</head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>THE Word of the Lord God to you who are called <hi>Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, [and to you that read the Common-Prayer.]</hi> You are wholly in <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> given up to it, <hi>[and ſo your dark Minds have the Common Prayer.]</hi> And ſuch would have a King to Reign, for there is that Nature that would have an Earthly King to Reign, in which Nature lodgeth the Murtherer.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>G. F.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Obſ. [<hi>But the Quakers Meſſages and Addreſſes to K.</hi> Ch. 2. <hi>and K.</hi> Ja. <hi>they are for having an Earthly King to Reign, and conſequently are by themſelves judged to be in the Nature, wherein lodgeth the Murtherer.</hi>]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48969:7"/>
               <head>Of the Great Succeſs that <hi>George For</hi> told <hi>Oliver</hi> he ſhould have had, if he had been Faithful; in a <hi>Letter</hi> to him, Dated <hi>11th.</hi> Month <hi>1657.</hi> See <hi>Council and Advice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 26, 27.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>OH <hi>
                           <hi>Oliver!</hi> Hadſt thou been Faithful,</hi> and thundred down <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit,</hi> the <hi>Hollander</hi> had been thy <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Tributers;</hi> and <hi>Germany</hi> had given up to have done thy <hi>Will;</hi> and the <hi>Spaniard</hi> had quivered like a <hi>Dry Leaf:</hi>—The <hi>King of France</hi> ſhould have bowed under thee his Neck; the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould have <hi>withered</hi> as in <hi>Winter;</hi> the <hi>Turk</hi> in all his <hi>Fatneſs</hi> ſhould have <hi>Smoaked:</hi> Thou ſhouldſt not have ſtood trifling about <hi>Small Things,</hi> but minded the Work of the Lord as he began with thee at firſt. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Men and true Hearts took part with thee: Oh take heed! and do not ſlight ſuch,</hi> leſt thou weaken thy ſelf, <hi>and not diſown ſuch as the Lord hath owned;</hi> thy <hi>Dread</hi> is not yet all gone, nor thy <hi>Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> Ariſe and come out, for hadſt thou been Faithful, thou ſhouldſt have <hi>crumbled Nations to Duſt;</hi> for that had been thy Place; now is thy <hi>Day of Tryal,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>G. F.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>The Succeſs here ſpoken of ſhould have befallen him by means of his Armies, wherein ſober Men and True Hearts took part with him; ſuch he exhorts not to ſlight, nor diſown ſuch as God had owned. Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to this he ſaith (in his Paper againſt Kingly Government,</hi> pag. 27. <hi>Why did you put out ſuch as fear God out of the Army, which might have been a Bleſſing to the Lord in their Generation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>This ſhews, That in <hi>G. F's</hi> Judgment (who pretends himſelf</hi> Infallible) <hi>ſuch as Fear God, and</hi> Quakers, <hi>might fight, and that it was ill done to put ſuch out of the Army.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>This following Letter ſhews that <hi>G. F.</hi> approved of <hi>Olivers Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> about which he gives him and his Souldiers Charge, <hi>p. 36, 37.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THou ſhouldſt have invited all the <hi>Christians</hi> upon Earth in all Nations, that are againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> to thee; to comein and joyn with thee againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> for thou haſt had Authority, <hi>ſtand to it,</hi> looſe it not, nor abuſe it, nor let any other take thy <hi>Crown,</hi> and do not ſtand cumbring thy ſelf about <hi>Dirty Prieſts;</hi> — and thou haſt had Power over Nations, for Nations begin to be on heaps; and invite all them that profeſs againſt the <hi>Pope</hi> in all Nations, to joyn with thee againſt him; and do not looſe thy <hi>Dominion</hi> nor <hi>Authority,</hi> nor the <hi>Wiſdom of God,</hi> but with that thou may'ſt order all; [☞ <hi>That will keep thee ſingle in Heart and Mind to the Lord;</hi>] and let thy <hi>Souldiers</hi> go forth with a free willing Heart, that thou may'ſt <hi>Rock Natious as a Cradle;</hi> and keep
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48969:7"/>thou in the Fear of the Lord, and all the <hi>Soldiers,</hi> and them that are under thee. This is a <hi>Charge</hi> to thee in the Preſence of the Lord God, that thou, nor them may looſe the Dread of the Lord, [☞ <hi>for that ſtrikes a terror in the Hearts of all People</hi>] &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>I am a <hi>Lover of thy Soul and eternal Good, an Eſtabliſher of Righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>G. F.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>Is not this a Juſt Authority which ſo great a Prophet exhorts him to ſtand to, and not to looſe nor ſuffer any to take his Crown. And yet this Authority is to be defended and enlarged by Soldiers, who are charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to go forth with a free willing heart, and to keep in the fear of the Lord, which argues they were in the fear of the Lord; and ſo either</hi> Quakers <hi>or as good as</hi> Quakers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>In another Letter the ſame <hi>G. F.</hi> ſalutes <hi>Oliver</hi> thus, <hi>p.</hi> 27.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Dear Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BE ſtill and in the Councel of God ſtand, and that will give thee Wiſdom that thou may'ſt fruſtrate Men's Ends, and calm Men's Spirits, <hi>and Crumble Men under;</hi> and ariſe and ſtand up in the Power of the Lord God, [☞ <hi>The Lambs Authority,</hi>] and fear not the Face of Man, but fear and dread the Lord God; then his Preſence, and Wiſdom, and Councel, thou ſhalt have to throw down the Rubbiſh, and quell all the bad Spirits under thy Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion;—therefore live in the Power of the Lord God, and feel his Hand that is ſtretched out over the Nations; for a Mighty Work hath the Lord to do in other Nations, and their <hi>Quakings</hi> and <hi>Shakings</hi> are but entring: So this is the Word of the Lord God to thee as a Charge to thee from the Lord God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>The ſame <hi>G. F.</hi> in the Name of the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Elect Aſſembly,—</hi>Known in the Nations by the Name of <hi>Quakers,</hi> To <hi>Rich. Cromwel</hi> Protector, p. <hi>47, 51.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Friend,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>LIve in <hi>God's Wiſdom</hi> if thou wilt reign in his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Strength,</hi> then none ſhall touch thee, and all them that fear God will be on thy ſide, and take thy Part, and be one with thee in all thy <hi>Sufferings,</hi> yea, till death. And <hi>G. For</hi> after ſix pages of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to him, concludes with theſe Words, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lord God Almighty preſerve thee in his <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Counſel,</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> over the Heads of his Enemies in thy ſelf, and in the World both.—And <hi>Friend,</hi> take heed of putting of honeſt godly Men out of the <hi>Army,</hi> [☞ <hi>or putting them out of their places, being Iuſtices of the Peace.</hi>] In ſo doing, thou wilt lame thy ſelf, and weaken thy Authority, and remove thy ſelf out of the Hearts of them that fear God.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>G. F.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:48969:8"/>
Obſ. <hi>He approves of his <hi>Power,</hi> and prays for his <hi>Victory over his Enemies</hi> in himſelf and in the World both,</hi> (And pray was not the King and his Party ſome of thoſe Enemies;) <hi>and he warns him of</hi> putting honeſt godly Men out of the <hi>
                     <hi>Army,</hi> as he had done his <hi>Father</hi> before.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>But when <hi>Richard</hi> was gone off the <hi>Stage,</hi> and the Officers of the Army in <hi>Power,</hi> then <hi>G. F.</hi> applies himſelf to them in theſe words,</head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>OH <hi>Friends!</hi> The <hi>Power</hi> of God ye have abuſed;—the <hi>Iuſt</hi> have been trodden under Foot,—who have been put out of the <hi>Army</hi> and <hi>Publick Services:</hi>—Now had you been Faithful in the <hi>Power</hi> of the Lord which once ſtirred, this Nation needed not have been affraid of any Nation upon the Earth; but your <hi>Dread</hi> would have ſounded over the World: But when you loſt the <hi>Power</hi> of God,—with which you had bruſhed at the Out-ſide of Things, then you turned againſt, and put them in Priſon (meaning the <hi>Quakers</hi>) that ſtruck at the Root.—And had you been Faithful to the <hi>Power</hi> of the Lord God which firſt carried you on, you had gone into the midſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> into their Land, to require the Blood of the <hi>Innocent</hi> that there had been ſhed, and have commanded them to have offered up their <hi>Inquiſition</hi> to you, and gone over them as the Wind, and knock'd at <hi>Rome Gates</hi> before now, and trampled <hi>Deceit</hi> and <hi>Tyrants</hi> under, and demanded the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf, and have commanded him to have offered up all his <hi>Torture-Houſes,</hi> and his <hi>Wracks,</hi> and <hi>Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> (which you ſhould have found as black as <hi>Hell</hi>) and broke up the <hi>Bars</hi> and <hi>Gates</hi> where all the Juſt Blood hath been ſhed, which ſhould have been required, and this you ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and this you ſhould have ſeen done in the <hi>Power,</hi> when you had been the <hi>Dread</hi> of all Nations, and you had been a <hi>Dread</hi> to them, and ſhould have ſet up a <hi>Standard</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and then you ſhould have ſent for the <hi>Turks Idol,</hi> the <hi>Mahomet,</hi> and plucked up <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and cryed up Chriſt the only King and Lord, and then People would have ſaid you had gone on in the Cauſe of God and his Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—And ſo if you had gone to have made <hi>Inquiſition</hi> for Blood, and to demand all the <hi>Inquiſitions</hi> abroad in the whole <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> whereby the Innocent Blood hath been ſhed; then all the People in the whole <hi>Chriſtendont</hi> that feared the Lord God would have ſaid with one conſent, <hi>Theſe are the Men that are gone out for God's Cauſe. Many valiant <hi>Captains, Souldiers,</hi>
                        </hi> and <hi>
                           <hi>Officers</hi> have been put out of the</hi> Army—becauſe of their Faithfulneſs to the Lord; — it may be for ſaying <hi>Thou</hi> to a ſingle Perſon, or for wearing their <hi>Hats,</hi> &amp;c.—Oh how are Men fallen from that which they were in at firſt! <hi>when Thouſands of us went in the Front of you,</hi> and were with you in the greateſt Heat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48969:8"/>—Oh what a <hi>Sincerity</hi> was once in the Nation! <hi>What a dirty naſty thing it would have been to have heard talk of a <hi>Houſe of Lords</hi> among them?</hi> Oh! how is the Sincerity choaked, ſmothered, and quenched, by the <hi>Fatneſs of the Earth,</hi> whereby they have forgot ten the Lord, and his <hi>Arm</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> that once carried them on.</p>
                     <p>And if ever you <hi>Souldiers</hi> and true <hi>Officers</hi> come <hi>again</hi> into the <hi>Rower</hi> (i. e. the <hi>Spirit</hi>) of God which hath been loſt, never ſet up your <hi>Standard</hi> till you come to <hi>Rome,</hi> and it be a top of <hi>Rome,</hi> then there let your <hi>Standard</hi> ſtand, and look at the <hi>Power</hi> of the Lord God, and never heed <hi>Gold</hi> nor <hi>Silver,</hi> for the Power of the Lord will give you enough, <hi>&amp;c. See</hi> To the Council of Officers, <hi>pag.</hi> 2, 3, 5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>G. F.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>He ſaith it was the <hi>Power</hi> of the</hi> Lord God <hi>that firſt carried them on, and had they been Faithful, they ſhould have required</hi> Innocent Blood <hi>of <hi>Spain,</hi>
                  </hi> and knock'd at <hi>
                     <hi>Rome Gates,</hi> and trampled <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants</hi> under, and demanded the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelf; and this they ſhould have done as an Army [in the Spirit and Power of God, which they had loſt] ſetting up a <hi>Standard</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> commanding the <hi>Turk,</hi> and crying up Chriſt the only King; [then all that feared the Lord</hi> [Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers as well as others] <hi>would have ſaid,—Theſe are the Men that are gone out for the Cauſe of God and his Truth]. Then he complains,</hi> That many valiant Captains, Souldiers, and Officers have been put out of the Army,—becauſe of their Faithfulneſs to the Lord; <hi>that is,</hi> for being <hi>
                     <hi>Quakers,</hi> as he intimates; Then he crys out, ſaying,</hi> Thouſands of us went in the <hi>Front</hi> of you. <hi>This was a time of <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity,</hi> when it would have been a <hi>dirty, naſty</hi> thing to have talked of <hi>a Houſe of Lords.</hi> He counſels them not to ſtop till they have ſet up their <hi>Standard</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and [never heed <hi>Gold</hi> nor <hi>Silver;</hi> for the Power of the Lord will give you enough; ſo <hi>E. Burrough</hi> ſays to the Army,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>God will give their [the Papiſts] falſlly conſecrated <hi>Veſſels</hi> and <hi>Treaſures</hi> a Spoil and Prey to you, if you be faithful.]</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Compare this with what they ſay in the other Column.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="remarks">
               <p>NOW I ſhall come to cite ſome Paſſages out of <hi>E. B's</hi> Books, he was one of their Chief Preachers, and in very great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem amongſt them, his Works they took care to reprint in <hi>Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi> but withal to expunge ſome Paſſages, and alter others, which diſcovered too much of his <hi>Oliverian</hi> and their <hi>Fighting Spirit.</hi> This Man is charged by <hi>Ieremiah Ives,</hi> to have juſtified the late War againſt the King, and is defended by <hi>Geo. Whitehead,</hi> another of their chief Preachers,) ſaying, <hi>Serious Search,</hi> p. 35, 36.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Thou art pleaſed to tell the World twice or thrice over, that we juſtifie the late Wars againſt the King:—And why ſo? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>E. B.</hi> in ſeverely warning the late <hi>Powers</hi> of their <hi>Down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal,</hi> did by way of Reproof tell <hi>Oliver</hi> what God had done for him,</q> even in the ſame Letter to him, wherein he plainly alſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48969:9"/>telleth him of the <hi>Great Oppreſſions which the People of God ſuffered under him,</hi> &amp;c. See <hi>(ſaith he) <hi>E. B's</hi> Works,</hi> from <hi>pag.</hi> 551. to <hi>pag.</hi> 583. how plainly and faithfully he did warn <hi>Oliver</hi> and thoſe Men then in Power, of their <hi>Overthrow. To be ſure <hi>E. Burrough</hi> was no <hi>Temporizer.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Now we are to ſee whether <hi>E. Burrough</hi> doth not Juſtifie the late War againſt the King. <hi>Counſel and Advice.</hi> Printed <hi>1659.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>In his Letters to <hi>Oliver,</hi>
                  </hi> Protector, May 1657. <hi>he hath theſe Paſſages,</hi> Pag. 4.</head>
               <p>THE Lord gave thee the Necks of Princes to tread upon,—and their Dominions to inherit, and thou waſt ſet a <hi>Ruler</hi> in much Dominion, and haſt ſavour in his Sight, and in the ſight of many People, who wiſhed well unto thee for a Bleſſing: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Victories honourable and remarkable was given unto thee, <hi>over them who had exalted themſelves againſt God, and ruled in Tyranny over his People; whom the Lord pittied, and thou an Inſtrument in his Band, waſt ordained by him to lead forth a People, whom he Bleſſed with thee, againſt a cruel People, and Generation of Oppreſſors, who exerciſed Tyranny over the Lord's Heritage, till they were taken away, and caſt out, and are a Reproach unto the Lord and his People unto this day; and even ſo ſhall all be that follow their Example, and are Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors and Tyrants over the Seed of God, as they were.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> Theſe Lines in Black Letter are all left out in his Works, <hi>p.</hi> 552.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>In another Letter to him he writes thus, dated <hi>September 1657. Pag. 16, 17.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IT is upon me, and alſo I am preſſed in <hi>Spirit</hi> thereunto, to give unto thee, even unto the <hi>Oliver,</hi> Protector, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect meaſure of thy Dominions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—Many Enemies thou haſt which watch over thee for Evil, and not for Good, who would rejoyce in thy overthrow. And firſt there is a People ſcattered through all theſe Nations, who are full of Wrath and ravening Envy towards thee, <hi>Even of thoſe known by the Name of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants Party;</hi> in whoſe Hearts, to this day, there is continual hatred, and evil ſurmiſing lodgeth againſt thee, and all thy Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring; and I believe—that dayly advantage they ſeek againſt thee, by ſubtle Conſpiracies and ſecret Plottings of Maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in their <hi>Evil</hi> Hearts, ſeeking by all means, if it be poſſible, how to be avenged, and not ſlipping any advantage how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge themſelves <hi>and the Cauſe of their King.</hi>—I know the Lord hath <hi>Curſed</hi> them and their Endeavours to this day, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48969:9"/>thou haſt had Dominion and Power given thee of God to bruiſe them and to break them to pieces; <hi>and what thou haſt done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their King ſhould not be reckoned againſt thée by the Lord, if now thou wert Faithful to what he requires of thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note, <hi>And promote their Cauſe,</hi> is put in inſtead of <hi>The Cauſe of their King,</hi>
                  </hi> p. 559. <hi>And the word <hi>blaſted</hi> is put in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Curſed.</hi> And all the Words in Black Letter are left out in his Works,</hi> p. 560.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>How he calls the <hi>Protector</hi> and his <hi>Party,</hi>
                  </hi> a People whom the Lord bleſſed, againſt a cruel People and Generation of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, <hi>that is, thoſe called the <hi>Malignant Party,</hi> that were for the <hi>King;</hi> he ſaith alſo,</hi> The Lord hath curſed them and their Endeavours to this day, <hi>and that if the Protector would own them,</hi> (the <hi>Quakers,</hi>) they would own him in the Face of all his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>the chief of which were then the</hi> King<hi>'s <hi>Party.</hi> How ſhould they do that without fighting?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>And in a Letter of his to the <hi>Protector</hi> and <hi>Council. 12th.</hi> Month, <hi>57.</hi> he ſaith, <hi>p. 23.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat! Hath the abundance of this Worlds Glory and its Treaſure quite overcome, and ſtoln away your Hearts wholly from all ſenſe and ſeeling of the unjuſt Sufferings of your Brethren (meaning the <hi>Quakers,</hi>) who have in times paſt, as faithfully as your ſelves, ſerved the Nation with their Lives and Eſtates, to the purchaſing of this Peace and Freedom out of the hands of <hi>Tyrants?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tyrants</hi> is left out, and the word <hi>Oppoſers</hi> put in its ſtead. <hi>E. B's works,</hi> p. <hi>563.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>
                  <hi>In another Letter to the</hi> Protector, <hi>which was given to him the</hi> 6th. <hi>Month,</hi> 1658. <hi>about a Month before his Death, he writes thus,</hi> p. 33.</head>
               <p>ARiſe and ſtand up for the Lord, and he will give thee ſtrength and Victory, and will make thy <hi>Horn</hi> as <hi>Iron,</hi> and thy <hi>Hoof</hi> as <hi>Braſs,</hi> to puſh down and tread under the <hi>High Places of Idolatry</hi> in all the <hi>Apoſtatiz'd Churches</hi> both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And as concerning thy War and Armies abroad in</hi> Spain; <hi>ſomething there is in it known to the Lord, ſeek not thine own Honour in it, but be Faithful, and leave the iſſue of all things to the Lord; make no Covenant with Idolaters, but tread down their Idol-Gods that they have ſet up; and hew down their Mountains in which their Confidence ſtands, and Plow up their ground, that the Seed may be ſown after thee. It's Honour enough to be the Lord's Plowman,</hi> p. 35. <hi>Theſe foregoing Lines in Black Letter, are left out in the reprinting of his Works,</hi> p. 568.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48969:10"/>
Obſ. <hi>How he exhorts the</hi> Protector to puſh down, and tread un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the High Places of Idolatry: <hi>and where?</hi> In all the Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd Churches, both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and others: <hi>And this he intimates is to be done by his Armies, and he would not have him</hi> to make any Covenant with Idolaters, <hi>&amp;c. Theſe are the Men that in their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration (ſince the King came in)</hi> deny both the Spirit, Principle, and Practice of them that uſe any Weapon to fight for Chriſt or his Government. <hi>And yet hear in the following Paſſage, how this <hi>E. Burrough</hi> declares to Governour <hi>Lockart</hi> and the Officers in the Name of the Lord, that if they went forth as an Army in that</hi> Spirit <hi>that was among the <hi>Quakers,</hi> they ſhould then overcome their Enemies, Take his own words as reprinted and not expunged, and ſo owned afreſh by <hi>G. F.</hi> [G. Whitehead] and their Party.</hi> 1672.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>
                  <hi>An Alarm ſounded in the <hi>Pope</hi>'s</hi> Borders. 1659 <hi>
                     <hi>E. B's</hi> Works.</hi> p. 536.</head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>AND this lay upon me to declare in the Name of the Lord (to Governour <hi>Lockart</hi> and his Officers,) That if they did enterpriſe any buſineſs, <hi>as they were an Army,</hi> in a <hi>Spirit</hi> in Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to us, and in that <hi>Spirit</hi> that did reject us, and deny us, and gainſay us; then ſhould they never proſper in any Enterpriſe whatſoever: But if they went on in any degree in the Fear of the Lord, <hi>and in that Spirit that was among us,</hi> then ſhould they overcome their Enemies, and none ſhould have Power over them to overcome them.</p>
                     <p>Obſ. <hi>What was it they were to do as an Army [in the Quakers Spirit?] See that in his Inſtructions to the</hi> Engliſh Army, <hi>&amp;c. in and about <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>AND that there be no more a looking back—till you have viſited <hi>Rome,</hi> and enquired after, and ſought out the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Blood that is buried therein; and <hi>avenge</hi> the Blood of the Guiltleſs through all the Dominions of the <hi>Pope,</hi> the Blood of the Juſt crys through <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and the time <hi>is come,</hi> that the Lord will ſearch it, and ſeek it out, and repay it, and it would be your Honour to be made uſe of by the Lord in any Degree in order to this Matter.—And this alſo believe, that the Lord will do it, or make way hereunto, even by you, the Men of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, if you be faithful, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 537.</p>
                     <p>What are theſe few poor Iſlands that you have run through, and laid many Mountains low? they are but little in compariſon of the great part of Chriſtendom in which Idolatry and great Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions do abound, which the Hand of the Lord is againſt, and which he will take Vengeance upon, p. 538.</p>
                     <p>But there are many Mountains in the way, wherefore hew down the <hi>Tops,</hi> ſtrike at the <hi>Branthes,</hi> make way, that the <hi>Ax</hi> may be laid to the <hi>Root</hi> of the <hi>Tree,</hi> that <hi>your Sword,</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48969:10"/>the <hi>Sword</hi> of the Lord may neither leave <hi>Root</hi> nor <hi>Branch</hi> of Idolatry, Oppreſſions, and Tyranny;—your Sword is to be lifted up againſt them. It is the Lord's Work, I know, to make Men truly Religious, but yet the Lord may work by you to break down the <hi>Bryars,</hi> and <hi>Thorns,</hi> and <hi>Hills,</hi> that have ſet themſelves againſt the Lord. <hi>P.</hi> 538. God will make <hi>their Riches and their falſly conſecrated Veſſels, and Treaſures, even a Spoil and a Prey unto you,</hi> if you be faithful, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 539.</p>
                     <p>Your work hath been, and may be honourable in its day,—and your <hi>Victory</hi> hath been of the Lord—So be low in your own Eyes,—and ſeek the Glory of God, and the Freedom of the Oppreſſed, and in that you will be Bleſſed, and proſper, till you have ſet up your <hi>Standard</hi> at the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> p. 540.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>I am a Lover of your Souls,—E. B.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>That both the <hi>Army-Sword,</hi> and the <hi>Sword of the Lord</hi> were not</hi> to leave Root or Branch of Idolatry. <hi>In ſo doing, he promiſes them Bleſſing and Proſperity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>The ſame <hi>E. Burrough</hi> to <hi>Rich. Cromwel</hi> choſen to be <hi>Protector,</hi> See <hi>Council and Advice,</hi> p. <hi>53.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>AND as for thy Father, the late Protector, great things and honourable did the Lord do for him in raiſing him up, and caſting out his Enemies before him; and giving him Victory and Power, and Renown through Nations; and we know the Lord ſhewed favour to him, and gave him <hi>Strength, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour,</hi> and a <hi>Right Spirit;</hi> and he was called of God into that great Work to ſubdue the grievous <hi>Tyrannies</hi> once ruling over <hi>Tender Conſciences,</hi> and to break down the great Oppreſſions which for Ages had cauſed the Juſt to groan, and the Lord was with him in Victory, and went before him, and was his <hi>Defence,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved him from great dangers; and from the Wills of all his Enemies, and made him proſperous againſt them all.—And as for thee who art now ſet up in his ſtead, we certainly believe that the Hand of the Lord is in this Matter, <hi>&amp;c. Note, <hi>Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> is left out, and the word <hi>Cruelty</hi> put in, in his Works,</hi> p. 574.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>As concerning the Armies abroad, let faithful and juſt Men that will not ſeek themſelves, be put in truſt, for the Army is of great Concernment to thee, to ſtand or fall through them, as to Man's account; and the War againſt</hi> Spain, <hi>be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to God in it, and let truſty Men have Authority, the Lord may accompliſh ſomething by it to his Honour, and to thine, if thou be meek and humble, and walk with the Lord, and to ſay no more about it, there is ſomething in it known to the Lord, and he may bring it to paſs in its Seaſon,</hi> p. 64.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>
                           <hi>London,</hi> 
                           <date>18th. 8th. <hi>Month,</hi> 1658.</date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe Lines in Black Letter are all left out in his Works,</hi> p. 580.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:48969:11"/>
Obſ. <hi>He ſaith that the Lord in caſting out his Fathers Enemies, and giving him Victory, did not only do <hi>great things,</hi> but <hi>honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> that he ſhewed him favour, and gave him a <hi>Right Spirit.</hi> [Is it not plain the Quakers held that God commanded a Right Spirit to Fight, and that Oliver was called of God thereto?]</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>
                  <hi>E. Burrough</hi> to the <hi>Protector</hi>'s Kind ed, his <hi>Wife</hi> and <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> p, <hi>37, 38.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Friends,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>REmember that by the Lord you were raiſed from a low Eſtate, — he gave you the Palaces of Princes, <hi>and threw out the High and Mighty before you, becauſe of their Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which was great in the Sight of the Lord.</hi> Oh! remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber this every one of you, — and be of a tender Spirit, — and exalt not your ſelves, — leſt the Lord caſt you down, and make your Name and Poſterity a Reproach, as he hath done many before you, <hi>even for that cauſe was the Generation of the Stewarts caſt out.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note, All theſe Words in Black Letter, are left out in his Works,</hi> p. 569.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>That he ſaith, for exalting themſelves in Pride,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>was the Generation of the <hi>Stewarts</hi> cast out, and their Palaces beſtowed on the</hi> Protector <hi>and his Family [And pray <hi>G. W.</hi> &amp;c. was not</hi> White-Hall <hi>one of thoſe Palaces?]</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Now let us hear what <hi>Francis Howgil</hi> ſaith in Juſtification of the late War. See his <hi>Advice to the Army, Committee of Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>1659.</hi> p. <hi>3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Long-Parliament againſt the late King, which in Man's account could be looked upon to be no other than <hi>Rebellion;</hi> yet God gave a ſignal Teſtimony to the one, while they ſtood in the Power of God, and againſt the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The antient Courtiers having found ſo much Eaſe and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit by the late King, turned all Cavaliers, and cryed up the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative of the King above Law and Equity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Setting that aſide wholly which all Good Government was intended for, as the Safety of the People, and fréedom from Oppreſſion, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and Vſurpation, and that none might be embondaged in the Worſhip of God; but when he (to wit the late King) and his Aſſiſtants ſought to inthral all, and Imbondage all, both in Civil and Eccleſiaſtical things, (as they were called,) the Long-Parliament and People that aided them at that time counted it no Treaſon to oppoſe him, ſeeing the End was not anſwered he ſhould have ſatisfyed; and God decided the Controverſie in over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing the one, and eſtabliſhing the other for a ſeaſon; yet many are ſo blind to this day; that they judge the Nation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be eſtabliſhed in Freedom without a King, as though ſuch a Name were eſſential only to Freedom, and without it could
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48969:11"/>not be obtained; but the Iudicious will ſee this Ignorance,</hi> &amp;c. —So now many are ſo doting on the Name of a Parliament, as though it were Eſſential, &amp;c. — and cry up the Privileges of Parliament, as the <hi>former</hi> did <hi>Prerogative,</hi> and would fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Name,—and loſe the Thing intended, though they be the Repreſentatives of the People to do good to the People, and not hurt, they are accounted as good Servants to God, but if they would—ſet up a particular Intereſt to the Imbondaging of the whole, and then cry up their Privileges to do what they liſt, <hi>Then it is no Rebellion in Gods Account, neither in the account of Iuſt Men, to call them away when they do not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Thing intended. And as for the</hi> Long-Parliament <hi>by whom God did Good Things, and Great Things,</hi> in the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing that Power which was deviated from the aforeſaid End <hi>(to wit) the late King,</hi> — What they did, they had the Approbation of God and Good Men; yet they went not through with the Work purpoſed and intended. <hi>Note, All theſe Lines in Black Letter are left out in <hi>F. H's</hi>
                  </hi> Works.</p>
               <p>When a Company of greedy hireling Prieſts came from <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter-ſhire</hi> to ſound their Trumpet in the Houſe, and to tell you they had not ingaged with the reſt of their Brethren in <hi>Cheſhire</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> with <hi>George B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oth,</hi> they were immediately called in, and thanks returned, as though they had done ſome great Service for the Nation <hi>that they joyned not in the Rebellion; but them who were your real Friends, called Quakers, who gave you and the Army intelligence about the late Inſurrection in</hi> Cheſhire, <hi>who were ſpoiled by the ſaid Rebels of their Goods,</hi> &amp;c—<hi>could never receive any ſatisfaction or incouragement from you,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Note, All the foregoing Lines in Black Letter are left out in <hi>F. H's</hi> Works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>He ſaith God gave a ſignal Testimony for the Parliament a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the late King: That it is no Rebellion to call them (who were in</hi> Power) <hi>away, when they do not perform the Thing they are intruſted for. That</hi> God <hi>did good and great things by the</hi> Long-Parliament, <hi>in overthrowing the late <hi>King;</hi> wherein they had the Approbation of God and good Men; that they who joyned with Sir</hi> George Booth, <hi>joyned in Rebellion, that at the ſame time, the</hi> Quakers <hi>were the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments real Friends, and gave them and the Army Intelligence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>See alſo <hi>E. Burrough to the new Committee of Safety. 1659.</hi> to the ſame purpoſe concerning <hi>Depoſing Governors.</hi> E. B's <hi>Works,</hi> p. <hi>593.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AND though ſome of you (preſent Rulers) be looked upon as great <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Tyrants</hi> in your dealing towards them, [i. e. <hi>the Parliament</hi>] — but alas! this is nothing, for the Lord doth not account as Men, — and if you were faithful
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48969:12"/>to what the Lord requires of you, in your Proceedings, what you have done unto them, [i. e. <hi>in turning them out,</hi>] ſhould not be reckoned on account againſt you, neither by God, nor Good Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Likewiſe ſee the Declaration of their Faith touching <hi>Governours,</hi> E. B's <hi>Works.</hi> p. 442. Printed 1672.</head>
               <p>WE believe that all Governors and Rulers ought to be accountable to the People and to the next ſucceeding Rulers for all their Actions which may be enquired into upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion; and that the chiefeſt of the Rulers be ſubject under the Law, and puniſhable by it if they be Tranſgreſſors, as well as the pooreſt of the People. [<hi>Note, This Article of their Faith they alſo printed in the year</hi> 71. <hi>in their Book called,</hi> The Principles of Truth, <hi>p.</hi> 51. <hi>But as I was not, ſo I am not willing any Obſervation ſhould be made thereon, and that for their ſakes.</hi>]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Now hear <hi>E. B's Advice to the Parliament of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of England,</hi> &amp;c. againſt Heriditary Government, <hi>6th. October 1659.</hi> [But after K. C. <hi>2.</hi> was reſtored, then they left all this Paper out in the Reprint of his Works:]</head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>AND while thus it hath been, in our Nation, that our Kings have attained to the Throne of Government Hereditarily, and by the Succeſſion of Birth,—and thus it hath continued for many Ages—and our Nation hath been under the Bonds of Slavery in this reſpect, even becauſe Men Govern'd that ought not;—and while Men for Earthly Honour—in Birth an Breeding have claimed to be Princes over us ſucceſſively, and to be choſen our Rulers according to Cuſtom, — and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of this the Free-born People have deeply ſuffered the cruel Oppreſſions of proud and ambitious ſelf-ſeeking Men, who have long Ruled for themſelves and not for the Lord, and have come into place of Authority otherwiſe than by Appointment and right Calling from the Lord, And thus the Government of our Nation hath been out of Courſe,—while great Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath remained upon the Hearts of the People, which hath ſo blinded them that they have not known their own Bondage, nor yet how to be redeemed into perfect Liberty, while they have ſubjected themſelves (through Ignorance) to be ruled by ſuch Men as had no right from God to that Place of Rule and Government.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>But now the Lord God our Deliverer hath begun to appear for the Freedom of the Nations, and hath ſhewed us the Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity and Bondage that our Fore-fathers have lived under, and we our ſelves been liable and ſubject to, by reaſon of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſtanding in a ſingle Perſon ſucceſſively, and we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48969:12"/>forced to live under the Authority of ſuch Men as had no right from God thereunto, as I have ſaid: And now our Eyes are opened to ſee better things, and we are in good Expectations that the Lord will Suddenly ſo appear as to free us from future Oppreſſions in this reſpect,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>And theſe things we are waiting for, to be brought to paſs in their Seaſon, and the Hand of the Lord will accompliſh it; if not by you, then even contrary to you. Therefore take this my Council even as you hope to proſper; for this I know from the Lord, upon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting or receiving hereof dependeth your Standing or your Fall, your Renown or perpetual Reproach; even your Bleſſing or your Curſe; and the time is at hand that many ſhall confeſs the Lord gave good Counſel to you by his Servant.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>E. Burr.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>That in his Judgment it was through Ignorance that the People ſubjected themſelves to</hi> Hereditary Governours, <hi>or ſuch as had no right to the Place of Rule, or to the Government, ſtanding in a</hi> Single Perſon ſucceſſively; <hi>and he reckons it a piece of Slavery the Nation hath long been under, that our Kings have attained to the</hi> Throne Hereditarily, <hi>and yet <hi>G. F.</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. <hi>(of late) tells the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament that their Hearts and Hands could ſeal to the Subſtance both of the Oaths of</hi> Allegiance <hi>and</hi> Supremacy. <hi>And <hi>G. F.</hi> ſaith,</hi> If he could take any Oath at all, upon any occaſion, he ſhould take the Oath of Allegiance, <hi>which Oath binds to the King, and his Heirs and Succeſſors. Now if this be not Contradiction and Temporizing, what is?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>See moreover <hi>G. F's Paper</hi> (taken out of the ſame Book, that the <hi>Abſtract againſt Kingly Government</hi> was taken) <hi>p. 42.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>To all ſuch as feed the</hi> Prieſts <hi>till they turn againſt them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE <hi>Black Preſbyterians</hi>—and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Cavaliers,</hi> which are ſtirring; you being out of the Power which firſt had Dominion over them; what now are <hi>Prieſts, Cavaliers, Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians,</hi> ſaying, Curſe you <hi>Meroz,</hi> that will not come to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Mighty! (meaning the Parliament,) and all the honeſt People in the Nation, to deſtroy them. And what! are they now bawling againſt you, as they have againſt the <hi>Quakers?</hi> Will no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſatisfie the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and the reſt, but Blood? Have they not been the ſtirrers up for War and Blood always? What now! are they ſo fat fed, that they curſe them that will not come to fight againſt the Parliament? Have you fed them ſo fat, that they kick againſt you like wild Horſes, that they ſnort, that there is ſuch a ſnorting among them againſt their Feeders? Have you ſed them like wild Bulls and Heifers, that now they run againſt you with their Horns? Surely the Fodderers of theſe have not well looked about them; have not theſe been called <hi>Miniſters
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48969:13"/>of the Goſpel?</hi> But now how comes it that they preach up War? Theſe are bad Cattle, Horſes, Heifers, and Bulls, that kick againſt their Fodderers. And run with their Horns againſt their Fodderers.—I muſt tell you the Sun is ſet upon all the Prieſts in this Nation, and ſuch as be like minded, and that is the Word of the Lord God to this preſent Age, and many more.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>G. F.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Hear now <hi>Iſ. Penington,</hi> an Eminent Writer among them, [and one of good repute,] to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Army,</hi> and all the <hi>well-affected in the Nation,</hi> who have been faithful to the <hi>Good Old Cauſe, 1659. p. 1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat there hath been a Backſliding and turning aſide from the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> even by the <hi>Army</hi> (who formerly were <hi>Glorious Instruments</hi> in the <hi>Hand</hi> of God) hath been lately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed. — The Name of God hath been Blaſphemed in the whole Earth, and that Holy Spirit and Power (which many Hearts can witneſs, was the <hi>Beginner</hi> and <hi>Carryer on</hi> of this <hi>Work</hi>) made a Scoff and Deriſion to the Enemies of Truth in theſe Nations, and in the Nations round about, who watched to ſee the Iſſue and Reſult of theſe things. The Controverſie was very great and eminent, and drew many Eyes upon it, the Lord was appealed to on both ſides to decide it, and many know that by his <hi>Preſence</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> in the <hi>Army</hi> the Stale was turned (even when they were very very low, and cryed out for Prayers, and made large Promiſes in the Days of their Diſtreſs;) yea, the Lord did not deſert the Army, but heard their Prayers, and the Prayers of his <hi>People</hi> for them, carrying on the Deliverance, until he had given a perfect Victory into their Hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>That by the <hi>Lord's Preſence</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> in the</hi> Army, <hi>the Controverſie was decided, and the</hi> Army <hi>made Glorious Inſtruments for the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> was not then the Armies Cauſe once Juſt [in the Quakers Opinion] and their fighting lawful and approved of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>
                  <hi>Miles Halhead</hi> and <hi>T. S.</hi> two Eminent Men of their Miniſtry, follow with their moſt plain Teſtimony, <hi>Wounds of an Enemy,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>1656.</hi> p. <hi>23.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> ſaw the Army <hi>(who were made the <hi>Sword</hi> of the Lord—againſt Papiſts and Biſhops)</hi> would not ſubmit to the Covenant, they drew the Sword againſt them, and not prevailing in a firſt War, many of them joyned with the <hi>Papiſts and Biſhops, and the Common Enemy,</hi> (meaning the King.) And now an <hi>Oath of Abjuration</hi>—is tendred to them to Swear—who have been <hi>moſt faithful to the Common-wealth, and its Army, and have born the Brunt and Heat of the Day in the late Wars,</hi> with the peril of their Lives in the Field, and the loſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48969:13"/>of their Eſtates, againſt the <hi>Popiſh, Prelatical,</hi> and <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Party.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hath this Generation witneſſed the Word of the Lord to be true above many Generations? before whoſe Eyes, <hi>and by whoſe Hands</hi> the Righteous God hath executed his Dreadful Judgments on the Enemies of his Elect; — hath he deſpiſed the Image of the King and Princes, and Nobles, and the great Ones, — and poured forth their Blood as Water on the Earth, and made them a fearful deſolation, in the Cauſe of his People, and of Juſtice, and of Equity.—In the Iniquities that they have committed, and in the Sins wherewithal they have Sinned, hath He cut them off, and made them the dreadful Examples of his Vengeance, p. 75, 76.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>The Contents of this is plain to every capacity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Take alſo <hi>George Roffs</hi> Teſtimony, another of their Miniſtry.</head>
               <p>TO thee <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> thus ſaith the Lord, I had choſen thee among the thouſands of the Nations, to execute my Wrath upon my Enemies, and gave them to thy <hi>Sword, with which I fought,</hi> for the Zeal of my own Name, and gave thee the Enemies of my own Seed to be a Curſe and a Reproach for ever, and made thee an Inſtrument againſt them, — and many have I cut down by my Sword in thy Hand, that my Wrath might be executed on them to the utmoſt. See <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>Here the Lord is repreſented fighting with <hi>Oliver's Sword</hi> against God's Enemies. I think here is Juſtification ſufficient of the late Wars, enough to make <hi>George Whitehead</hi> (and thereſt) aſhamed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Hear again <hi>E. Burrough</hi> and <hi>F. Howgil</hi> pleading the <hi>Quakers</hi> Faithfulneſs to the <hi>Common-Wealth's Intereſt,</hi> and bringing to Mind the utter Deſtruction of the <hi>Biſhop's</hi> and <hi>King's Power,</hi> as of a ſtone ſunk into the Sea, which riſeth not again.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>To <hi>Henry Cromwel</hi> and his <hi>Council.</hi> The Viſuation of</hi> Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 21, 22.</head>
               <p>YOU have endeavoured to give ſentence of Baniſhment of us out of your Nation, who are free-born <hi>Engliſh-Men, and have always been faithful and true to the Common-Wealths Intereſt from firſt to laſt even until now.</hi>— What became of all the Perſeccutors of old? <hi>What became of the Biſhops? What became of that Power that held them up, are they not all ſunk as a Stone into the Sea, and become a Reproach.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>
                  <hi>Again <hi>E. B.</hi> to the</hi> Heads,—Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 19.</head>
               <p>If ſuch you uphold by a Law—which act thoſe things the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſpeaks againſt—God will lay your Honour in the duſt, and caſt you out of the Seat of Judgment; <hi>
                     <hi>as he hath done the Power of the King and Biſhops before you.</hi> Note, All the Lines in black Leter are left out in his Works,</hi> p. 84, 85, 86.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:48969:14"/>
               <head>Let us now hear News out of the <hi>North,</hi> &amp;c. A Book ſet out by <hi>G. F.</hi> and written (as he ſaith) <hi>from the Mouth of the Lord. 1655.</hi>
               </head>
               <floatingText type="letter">
                  <body>
                     <p>DReadful is the Lord and Powerful, who is coming in his Power to execute true Judgment upon all you Judges, and to change all your Laws ye Kings.— All you Rulers muſt down and ceaſe,—You muſt be cut down with the ſame Power that cut down the King who reigned over the Nation; in whoſe Family was a <hi>Nurſe</hi> for <hi>Papiſts</hi> and for <hi>Biſhops,—Judges,</hi> and <hi>Juſtices,— Beaſt</hi> and <hi>Falſe Prophet;</hi> the Lord God will pour out his Plagues upon you, the Lord of Hoſts hath ſpoken it, and except you repent you ſhall all likewiſe periſh, and be conſumed as the King was, and periſh with the ſame Power. The Lord God hath ſent his Prophets oft to tell you ſo, p. 18, 19</p>
                     <p>The World knows me not, but I teſtifie the Truth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>G. Fox.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>What Man could have wrote more againſt a <hi>King</hi> and <hi>King: ly Government,</hi> than this <hi>G. Fox</hi> hath done, and that in the Name and Authority of the</hi> Lord <hi>of Lords, and</hi> King <hi>of Kings, (as he ſaith,) and yet no ſooner was the King inveſted in his Fathers <hi>Throne,</hi> but the ſaid <hi>G. Fox,</hi> through <hi>Deceit, Fear,</hi> and <hi>Flattery,</hi> writes a quite contrary Language.</hi> See the other Column p. 1, 2, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Again hear alſo what <hi>G. Fox</hi> and other <hi>Quakers</hi> tell us in the <hi>Weſt anſwering to the North,</hi> Writ <hi>1656</hi> the next year after <hi>News out of the North,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>One <hi>Ier. Ives</hi> (taking notice of their frequent Abuſes to others about the late War) cites a Paeſſage of theirs out of <hi>E. B's</hi> Works in Juſtification of the late Wars; and further ſaith, The Book in</hi> The Weſt anſwering to the North, <hi>p.</hi> 79, 89 94, 95, 96, 97. <hi>hath much to the ſame purpoſe, which (ſaith he)</hi> I am unwilling to write out, becauſe I am not willing to expoſe you. <hi>
                     <hi>G. Whitchead</hi> replies thus in his <hi>Serious Search,</hi> p.</hi> 37. I cannot but obſerve the Man's Diſſimulation and baſe Inſinuation in this implicite kind of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing us, hereby to render us more ſuſpicious and obnoxious than if he had dealt plainly; <hi>meaning, than if he had printed thoſe Paſſages; ſome of which here follow; by which the Reader may ſee ſomewhat of <hi>G. W's</hi> Diſingenuity and Serpentine Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>TO what purpoſe have been the hangings by the Neck,—and other exemplary puniſhments executed on Judges, Juſtices, and Miniſters of State for Arbitrary acting;—Why was <hi>Straf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford's</hi> Head cut off, and <hi>Canterbury's,</hi> and <hi>Charles Stewart's</hi> as <hi>Traytors,</hi> for endeavouring to ſubvert the fundamental Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 78.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles Stewart</hi> and his Lords committed Men, as <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:48969:14"/>aforeſaid, and early he heard of it in Parliament:—and for his other Arbitrary Actions, and what followed thereupon— and befel him in particular needs not be mentioned, being recorded every where in the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Miſery</hi> of the late Wars, and the Deſtruction of <hi>Him</hi> and his <hi>Family;</hi> the dreadful and ſad Examples of <hi>His Righteous Iudgments</hi> who reuders to every one according to his Deeds, <hi>p.</hi> 79.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>Becauſe ſome of their Friends were committed, and in the</hi> Warrant <hi>no mention made of the Protector or his Authority, they far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther write thus;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth not here appear from the Grave, the <hi>Spirit</hi> that was in <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> and his <hi>Fellow Traytors;</hi> who being within the Juriſdiction of this <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> took upon them to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionate divers Men to treat with <hi>Charles Stewart</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed <hi>Traytor</hi> of the Government, <hi>p.</hi> 89. Call to mind the former days, and let the things that are paſt come into your Remembrance even what this Generation would have done, their <hi>Synod,</hi> and <hi>Accomplices</hi> to Conſcience, and to whom this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration joyned (in the years 1648. and 50. and ſo forwards) even with the Common Enemy, <hi>
                     <hi>Charles Stewart,</hi> &amp;c. p.</hi> 94. And forget not the wonderful Deliverances from them; all which the Right Hand of the Lord effected, <hi>&amp;c. p.</hi> 95. Multitudes of People flock'd out of the City to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> to complain of their ſufferings,—which <hi>Charles Stewart</hi> called Tumults,—and by the Guard one of them was ſlain; at the place of the ſhedding of whoſe Blood was <hi>Charles Stewart's Head ſtruck off,</hi> and his <hi>Blood</hi> poured forth on the ground, <hi>
                     <hi>A remarkable Record of the Righteous Iudgments of God,</hi> p.</hi> 96, 97.</p>
               <p>And this his Law (Judge <hi>Nicholas</hi>) ſtanding in his own Will, —is leſs to be endured,—than in any of the Judges and Chief Juſtices that have gone before him, whom Juſtice hath cut off for Arbitrarineſs, or in <hi>Strafford, Canterbury, Charles Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wart,</hi> or any of theſe latter Generations. — And the <hi>Legiſlative Authority</hi> that made him a Judge, and the Righteous Ends of the Wars for Liberty and Law, in which he appeared, and theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Servants of the Lord, who have been all of them always faithful to the honeſt Intereſt of the Nation, and many of them for it have drawn the Sword, and fought in the Field from firſt to laſt, <hi>p.</hi> 102.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>Here that what they ſay concerning the King, is ſaid not only as the Opinion of others, but as what they alſo approve, ſaying, That thoſe things were remarkable Records of the Righteous Judgments of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>With what ſtrange kind of Confidence did <hi>G. W.</hi> write, when he ſaid, that if <hi>I. Ives</hi> had printed the foregoing Paſſages, they would not have rendred them ſo <hi>Suſpicious</hi> and <hi>Obnoxious,</hi> as his bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48969:15"/>mentioning the Book and Pages did. And though he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude and blind their</hi> Proſelites <hi>with ſuch deceitful and Fig leaf covers; yet certainly he will not dare to do ſo before Authority, but rather down upon his Knees and beg Pardon for his Audaciouſneſs and Inſolence, in ſpeaking ſo ſlightingly of ſuch ſtrange and prodigious Sayings as are before cited. And I wiſh him no more harm for all his Faults and falacious Doings, than an humble Submiſſion and Acknowledgment for the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Now let us hear <hi>E. Burrough</hi> bemoaning <hi>Oliver</hi> after his Death. <hi>A Teſtimony againſt a great Idolatry.</hi> This alſo is owned by <hi>G. F. G. W.</hi> and their <hi>Party,</hi> and is to be read in his Works, <hi>1672.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the midſt of my Conſiderations, a Pity ſtruck through me for once Noble <hi>Oliver</hi> that is now dead,—and I was grieved he ſhould be thus abuſed, being dead, by ſuch a ſtir about an Image made of him,—and I began to recal my former acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with him, and the former dealings of God towards him, and <hi>what a gallant Instrument for the Lord he once was,</hi> and how many <hi>Glorious and Noble Victories God once gave him,</hi> and what good Parts, and what a <hi>Gallant Spirit</hi> there was once in him,—and my Spirit run through many ſuch things with a great deal of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs and pity; and then ſaid I, Alas! Alas! is it ended all in this? All his <hi>ſormer good Service for God and the Nations,</hi> all his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories and good Actions, and his beating down <hi>Superſtition?</hi> Is this the end of it all, the making of an Image,—Is it all ended here? And is this the End and final Farewel of once <hi>Noble Oliver?</hi> p. 460.</p>
               <p>Alas for him! who was once a great Inſtrument in the Hand of the Lord, to break down many Idolatrous Images, — and did not once his Children, Officers, and his Brave Soldiers, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, pull down all the Images, and Croſſes, and all ſuch Popiſh Stuff where ever they met with it?—And ſhall we have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Repreſentation of once <hi>Noble Cromwel?</hi> Is his Life and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Glory and Nobleneſs ſhadowed with the ſight of a dead I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 461.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>This might ſerve for a piece of a</hi> Funeral Oration <hi>for once</hi> Noble Oliver; what a gallant Inſtrument for the Lord he once was! And how many Glorious and Noble Victories God once gave him, what good Parts, and what a gallant Spirit there was once in him! He had brave Soldiers and Army! <hi>And I pray was not this</hi> Noble Oliver <hi>and his brave Soldiers of that one ſort of People that profecuted War againſt the King; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſuch, <hi>E. B.</hi> ſaith,</hi> There is Guilt to be charged, <hi>See his</hi> Viſitation to the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 12. [<hi>And notwithſtanding the High Praiſes the Quakers gave of <hi>D. C.</hi> after his Death; yet when K. C. came in, then they compared him to</hi> Ahab, Haman, <hi>and</hi> Pharaoh
<note n="*" place="margin">Truth's Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ractor of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1660. p. 28, 31, 41.</note>, <hi>was not this done to flatter with the then Government,</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48969:15"/>that too by ſpeaking evil of the Dead! Oh moſt diſingenuous and unworthy Men!]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This <hi>E. B.</hi> was not a greater Friend to</hi> Oliver, <hi>and an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauder of him and his Armies brave Exploits; but he was as great a Decryer and Condemner of the</hi> Cavaliers <hi>and that Party. See</hi> A Trumpet of the Lord Sounded, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1656. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>To all you who are and have been always Enemies to the very appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Righteouſneſs who are called <hi>Delinquents</hi> and <hi>Cavaliers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THus ſaith the Lord, my Controverſie is againſt you, even my Hand in Judgment is upon you already, and you are become curſed in all your Hatchings and Endeavours, and from time to time my Hand hath been againſt you in Battel,</hi> &amp;c.—<hi>and though my Hand hath been evidently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you; yet to this day you remain in Rebellion in your Minds, in hatching Murder and Cruelty in your wicked Hearts, and though your Kings, and Princes, and Nobles, have been cut off in Wrath, and your cruel deſperate In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions and Plots of Wickedneſs (conceived in your curſed Womb) have been broken, and you cut ſhort in your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; yet you repent net, nor will you ſee how you are given to be a Curſe and a Deſolation, and a Prey in Houſes, and Lands, and Perſons, to them, whom I raiſed againſt you, and gave power over you, yet you are hardned, and your Cruelty in the perſecution of my Servants cannot be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured; where you have any power you ſmite with the</hi> Fiſt of Wickedneſs, <hi>and count it your Glory to deſpiſe my Name; in the Vallies of</hi> Vain-Hopes <hi>you feed, and on the Mountains of</hi> Fooliſh Expectation; <hi>and conceive in your cruel Womb of Tyranny the overthrow of the Nations, but in the bringing forth your ſelves are overthrown, and it is not for well-doing that you ſuffer; but my Hand is againſt you, and my Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are upon you, and except you repent, ſhall continue on Earth with you, and follow you, and purſue you to the</hi> Lake of Deſtruction, <hi>where there is no Repentance; and you and your Kings, and Lordly Power (by which you have thought to excrciſe Lordſhip over my Heritage) ſhall be enſlaved by the Devil in the Pit of Darkneſs, in everlaſting Bondage; where he ſhall reign your Lord and King for evermore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>That the whole Paper out of which the foregoing is extracted, is left out in the Reprint of <hi>E. B's</hi> Works,</hi> p. 100. <hi>Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he writ in the Epiſtle thus;</hi> Given under my Hand, and Seal'd by the Spirit of the Eternal God. <hi>And in</hi> p. 90. <hi>the word</hi> King <hi>is left out. And alſo in his Anſwer to the</hi> Apprentices Petition, 1659. <hi>Theſe followinging Lines are all left out,</hi> p. 609.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Would you bring in a ſtrange Nation, even</hi> Tyrants,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48969:16"/>
                  <hi>and their Adherents to devour the Land, and even to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy your ſelves and your City; would you ſet up an</hi> oppreſſing Monarchy, <hi>which the Land hath once</hi> ſpued forth; <hi>theſe things are to be doubted, that if your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns did prevail, the Fruit of your Work would tend thereunto.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>And notwithſtanding they in their Declaration given to the King, <hi>Jannuary 1660. Teſtifie that the Spirit of Chriſt which leads them into all Truth will never move them to Fight and War againſt any Man with Outward Weapons. Yet E. B.</hi> being moved of the Lord (as he ſaith) by his Spirit thereunto, gives forth thus, To the preſent diſtracted Nation of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>1659.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE have choſen the Son of God to be our King, and he hath choſen us to be his People, <hi>and He might command thouſands and ten thouſands of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants at this Day to fight in his Cauſe; He might lead them forth and bring them in, and give them Victory over all their Enemies, and turn his Hand upon their Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors;</hi> but yet his Kingdom is not of this World, neither is his Warfare with Carnal Weapons.— <hi>neither hath He choſen us for that end, neither can we YET believe that He will make uſe of us in that way; though it be his only Right to Rule in Nations, and our Heirſhip to Poſſeſs the uttermoſt Parts of the Earth, but for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> we are given up to bear and ſuffer all things for his Names-ſake, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 8.</p>
               <p>We are Friends to any appearance of Good that may come forth in Truth and Sincerity, and as Righteouſneſs doth appear in any, we are ready to joyn with it in our Prayers and Deſires; <hi>yea, and otherwiſe,</hi>—we ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce therein, <hi>and add our help thereunto that it may proſper,</hi> for the Eſtabliſhing of Righteouſneſs in the Earth; our all is not dear unto us, though hitherto we have been ſilent, and not meddling with this Party or the other, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> 1. <hi>This was publiſhed in the Name of the</hi> Quakers, <hi>and ſubſcribed by</hi> [J. P. <hi>and</hi>] <hi>many [others].</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> 2. <hi>All the Lines in <hi>Black Letter</hi> are left out in <hi>E. B's</hi> Works, Printed</hi> 1672. p. 603. <hi>[Their deſign therein is plain, they having writ contrary thereto upon the turn of times.] and the words <hi>and our help thereunto,</hi> are altered, as may be ſeen,</hi> p. 606. <hi>and in</hi> p. 662. <hi>
                     <hi>Theſe words, Tyrants ſhall not have Power over you,</hi> are left out. And</hi> p. 600. <hi>
                     <hi>Thy Kings.</hi> And</hi> p. 605. <hi>
                     <hi>With Kings</hi> are left out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>He ſays, He</hi> [the Son of God] <hi>might command Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48969:16"/>and ten Thouſands of his Saints at this day to fight, but we cannot</hi> yet <hi>believe, that He will make uſe of us in that way, but</hi> for the preſent <hi>we are given up to bear and ſuffer,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>So that they were not then of that Mind, that the</hi> Spirit <hi>would never move them to fight.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>And having heard of their Preaching up <hi>Armies, Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Spoils,</hi> &amp;c. Let us hear a little farther of <hi>G. F's</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing the <hi>Parliament</hi> to Sequeſtrations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>
                     <hi>G. F.</hi> To the</hi> Parliament <hi>of the Common-wealth of</hi> England.</head>
               <p>LEt all thoſe <hi>Abby-lands, Gleab lands,</hi> that is given to the Prieſts, be given to the Poor of the Nation, and let all the great Houſes, Abbies, Steeple-houſes and <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall,</hi> be for <hi>Alms-houſes</hi> (or ſome other uſe) for all the <hi>Blind</hi> and <hi>Lame</hi> to be there. <hi>Again,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let all thoſe <hi>Fines</hi> that belong to <hi>Lords of Mannors</hi> be given to poor People, for Lords have enough. <hi>p.</hi> 8. 1659.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>And in their Papers ſent to the <hi>Parliament</hi> about <hi>Tythes, 1659.</hi> p. <hi>65, 63.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF you Query how ſhall the <hi>Impropriators</hi> be ſatisfied who bought the Tithes of the King? have you not his <hi>Parks</hi> and his <hi>Rents,</hi> have you not his <hi>Houſes</hi> to ſell and make up their Money and give them again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — You ſhould have ſold all the <hi>Gleab lands,</hi> and ſold all the <hi>Bells</hi> (ſaving only one in a Town,) and Colleges and their Lands, and given them all to the Poor of the Nation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If you Query, How you ſhould do with the <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priators?</hi> ſell all the <hi>Gleab lands,</hi> and the <hi>Bells,</hi> except one in a Town, or two in a City (to give notice of Fire,) and all the late King's <hi>Parks</hi> and his <hi>Rents,</hi> that had <hi>Tenths,</hi> and ſold the <hi>Tythes,</hi> to make up theſe to give to the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriators</hi> that have bought <hi>Tythes,</hi> and the <hi>Abbies,</hi> and the <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> which much of the <hi>Tythes</hi> were given to; if you do intend to ſatisfie the Nation, and deny your ſelves of his <hi>Parks, Houſes,</hi> and <hi>Rents;</hi> ſo let them be ſold, and the <hi>Colleges</hi> ſold, and all the <hi>Tythes</hi> that belong to them thrown down, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 59. And you may ſell all the <hi>Gleab lands, Abby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> and <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> and <hi>Nunneries,</hi> and <hi>Kings Rents,</hi> and his <hi>Houſes,</hi> and the <hi>Bells</hi> to pay the <hi>Impropriators,</hi> who have bought the <hi>Tythes</hi> of Kings, let <hi>their Rents and Parks</hi> be ſold to pay them again, and let the Earth be reſtored again to its place; and they that have bought them of <hi>Colleges,</hi> let the <hi>Gleab-lands</hi> be ſold to pay them; So let the Earth be Redeemed.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="excerpts">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48969:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>G, Fox</hi> HIS JUDGMENT Concerning Kingly Government, ſince the King was <hi>Reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi> Declar. <hi>P.</hi> 3, 4.</head>
            <p>AND now becauſe ſeveral of you, who are moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are not acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with our Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Practices, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have known our Innocency and Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings,—and that no Prejudice were let in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Minds from others Words, which proceed from ſecret Envy, Malice, and Hatred, and not from any juſt Ground they have againſt us.—We do therefore Declare, to take off all Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, Fears, and Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions of our Truth and Fidelity to the King and theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Governors, <hi>That our Intentions and Endeavours are, and ſhall be Good, True, Honeſt, and Peaceable towards them, and that we do Love, Own, and Honour the King and the preſent Governours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:48969:6"/>
Obſerve, <hi>It is to be noted, That this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of <hi>G. For's,</hi>
               </hi> &amp;c. <hi>was delivered to the King the very next Month after he came in, ſo early were they in their</hi> Temporizing, <hi>that at the firſt reading of this among the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, <hi>they had writ, That they were his <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Subjects,</hi> and they had ſuffered much, as himſelf had done.</hi> Which Words were highly oppoſed by one of the Aſſembly, who told them, <hi>That if they put it out in the Name of the</hi> Quakers, <hi>he would Print againſt it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon thoſe Words were left out, and the Book put forth in the Name of <hi>G. F. and Others,</hi> that ſubſcribed it, in behalf of themſelves and thoſe in the <hi>Same <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> with them.</hi> How cunning was this <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription! For who would have thought</hi> that by thoſe in the <hi>
                  <hi>Same <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> was not meant every</hi> Quaker? <hi>And yet they meant only thoſe that were of the ſame Mind with the</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribers, <hi>which many were not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>II. Obſerve, <hi>Behold here the Man who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King's</hi> Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi>declared them</hi> Traytours againſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48969:6"/>Chriſt who cryed for an Earthly King, and the true Chriſtians will not have any more Kings among them, but Chriſt! <hi>Are they not in their own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment become Apoſtates? for now they ſay,</hi> They love, own, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour an Earthly King. <hi>And in their Viſit. to the King,</hi> p. 7. <hi>ſay to him,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IF thou take ſome ſpeedy courſe for the repealing and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king void thoſe Cruel Laws.— haply thou mayſt be as <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſtand in the gap'twixt God and thy People.</p>
            <p>[<hi>Did the Quakers verily think that K.</hi> C. <hi>was like to be aſecond</hi> Moſes, <hi>or did they ſay ſo only to daub and flatter him?</hi>]</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again in the Tryal of <hi>G, Fox</hi> in</hi> 1664. p. 8. 10. <hi>he ſaith, (the Oath of Allegiance being ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred to him,)</hi> That if he could take any Oath at all, upon any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, he ſhould take that Oath: <hi>And alſo ſaid,</hi> He honoured all Men, much more the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh Groſs Diſſimulation! What temporizing is this? What unheard of Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie is here? Will this Fig-leaf Garment cover the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of this</hi> Guide<hi>'s Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Perfidiouſneſs from thy Diſcerning and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure? I ſuppoſe not. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, more of this thou mayſt ſee in what follows.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48969:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>G. F. G. W.</hi> and their <hi>Party's Declaration</hi> in the Year <hi>1660.</hi> after the King came in, <hi>p. 2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL Bloody <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciples</hi> and <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices</hi> we (as to our own particular) do ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny, with all Outward Wars, and Strife, and Fightings with Outward Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons for any End, or under any pretence whatſoever.</p>
               <p>Obſerve. <hi>Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this, <hi>G. F.</hi> and <hi>E. Burrough</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to direct and principle <hi>Oliver</hi> and <hi>Richard,</hi> and the</hi> Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers <hi>and</hi> Soldiers <hi>what to do, and how, viz.</hi> That they ſhould go forth with a free wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Heart, and not ſtop till they come at <hi>
                     <hi>Rome,</hi> and blames them for turning, and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them not to turn</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Men <hi>and</hi> True Hearts <hi>out of the</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, <hi>and to require the <hi>Blood</hi> that hath been ſhed in the</hi> Inquiſition <hi>of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Rome:</hi> and that the <hi>Quakers</hi> were ſome of thoſe</hi> True learts, <hi>appears by thoſe other words of <hi>G. F's</hi> expoſtulating,</hi> Why ſuch as feared God and trembled at his Word ſhould be put out of the Army,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48969:7"/>which might have been a Bleſſing to the Lord in their Generation.</p>
               <p>And in page 3. of the ſame <hi>Declaration,</hi> they ſay thus; <hi>So thoſe that uſe any Weapon to fight for Chriſt, or for the Eſtabliſhing of his Kingdom or Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both the</hi> Spirit, Principle, <hi>and</hi> Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice <hi>in that we deny.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet theſe ſame Men (<hi>viz. <hi>G. F.</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>E. B.</hi>) <hi>would that the</hi> Officers <hi>and</hi> Souldiers <hi>ſhould have ſet up their <hi>Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard</hi> a Top of <hi>Rome,</hi> and have ſent for the <hi>Turks Idol,</hi> plucked up <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and cryed up Chriſt the only King.</hi> Oh wonderful!</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Again ſee the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Plea, 1661.</hi> How peaceable the <hi>Quakers</hi> are, and have always been <hi>p 7.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NO better Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony can be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of us and of our peaceableneſs (and that we ſhall not Plot nor Rebel againſt the King) than Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience it ſelf; Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience is the beſt Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that we are pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceable, and free from <hi>Plotting</hi> and <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion;</hi> for we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been ſo ſince we were a People, both before and ſince the <hi>King</hi> came in.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:48969:8"/>
Obſ. <hi>Theſe peaceable Men not only approve of what the</hi> Army <hi>did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Party,</hi> but would have them to continue <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> in the</hi> Army, <hi>and to enterpriſe the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Turk</hi> in their Spirit, and to invite all that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Pope</hi> to take part with them; and they promiſe the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector,</hi>
                  </hi> that if he would own them, they would own him in the <hi>
                     <hi>Face of all his Enemies</hi> Counſel and Advice</hi> p. 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And <hi>Francis How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil</hi> ſays,</hi> It was a good thing that the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> overthrew the late <hi>King;</hi> and that it is no <hi>Rebellion</hi> to call away <hi>[by which he means to <hi>Depoſe</hi>]</hi> thoſe in <hi>Power</hi> that perform not their <hi>Truſt</hi> for the Good of the <hi>
                     <hi>People.</hi> See more of this hereafter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Hear farther what <hi>G. F. &amp;c.</hi> ſay to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> after the riſing of the <hi>Fifth Monarchy Men,</hi> p. 2.</head>
               <p>AND now that we ſhould be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned amongſt a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple whoſe <hi>Principle is to Fight,—and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge themſelves;</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48969:8"/>which aſtoniſhes all them which know it. I believe your own Conſciences tell you that we are harmleſs, and would do you no harm,—but wiſh your Good, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It's known that thoſe you have numbred us amongſt, never denyed the bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of <hi>
                     <hi>Sword,</hi> nor <hi>Outward Weapons;</hi>
                  </hi> but whoſe <hi>Principle is to avenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>Could any Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple declare themſelves more for fighting than they did? How ſhould <hi>Oliver</hi> keep his <hi>Crown</hi> but by <hi>fighting?</hi> How did he get it, but by <hi>fighting?</hi> How ſhould the Army ſet up their <hi>Standard</hi> a top of <hi>Rome,</hi> but by <hi>fighting?</hi> How require the <hi>Blood</hi> that has been ſhed in the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> but by <hi>fighting?</hi> In ſhort, What ſhould Men do with <hi>Swords,</hi> but to <hi>fight,</hi> and yet they were not only to wear their <hi>Swords,</hi> but to cut down <hi>Idolaters</hi> with them, and their <hi>Sword</hi> was to be the <hi>Sword</hi> of the Lord in their Hand. And <hi>E. Burrough</hi> in expreſs for</hi> Avenging the <hi>Blood</hi> of the Guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs through all the Dominions of the <hi>
                     <hi>Pope,</hi> and exhorts the</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:48969:9"/>Army <hi>to do this going forth in their</hi> (<hi>the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers) <hi>Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How dare theſe Men appeal to the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Council<hi>'s Conſciences, that they are harmleſs, and would do them no harm; when they not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly approve of what was done in the late War, but offered their Service to <hi>Oliver,</hi> to own him (if he would own them) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all his Enemies; and ſome of them gave Intelligence to the</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my <hi>againſt Sir <hi>George Booth,</hi> whoroſe to bring in the</hi> King. See p. 13. of this Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>And notwithſtanding all that <hi>E. B.</hi> and others have written in Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment's Cauſe</hi> againſt the <hi>King,</hi> yet at the <hi>King</hi>'s coming in, that is in the middle of <hi>May, 1660.</hi> then <hi>E. B.</hi> writes, (In his Book called, <hi>A Viſitation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 12.</hi>)</head>
               <p>IN the beginning there were but one ſort of People that were in capacity to raiſe and proſecute War againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and upon ſuch there is <hi>Guilt</hi> to be charged in the Sight of God; who have foregone their <hi>Principles,</hi> and been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful both to God and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48969:9"/>Men. And as for us who are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> we are clear from the Guilt of all his Sufferings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>How often do they blame the</hi> Protector <hi>and others for putting of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and godly Men out of the Army; It may be becauſe they cannot put off their Hats,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and yet tell the King,</hi> They have ſuffered all along becauſe they would not take up Carnal Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons to fight withal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any, and are thus made a Prey upon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>(ſay they)</hi> we are the Innocent Lambs of Chriſt, and cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge our ſelves. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration,</hi> p 6. <hi>given forth under our Names, and in behalf of the whole Body of the Elect People of God who are called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>G. For, R. Hub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berthorn, I. Stubs, F. Howgil, G. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts, L. Fell, S. Fiſher, H. Fell,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Farther in the</hi> Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript <hi>thus:</hi> And all Wars and Fightings with Carnal Weapons we do deny, who have the Sword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>This the People cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers</hi> do witneſs to all the</hi> World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Again in</hi> P. 4. And this is both our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and Practice, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48969:10"/>hath been from the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, ſo that if we ſuffer as ſuſpected to take up Arms, or make War againſt any, it is without any ground from us, for it neither is, nor ever was in our hearts ſince we owned the Truth of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall we ever do it, becauſe it is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Spirit of Chriſt, his Doctrine, and the Practice of his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe words of theirs may ſerve for a</hi> Reply <hi>to an</hi> Anſwer <hi>they make to an</hi> Objection, <hi>that many of them have been in the Army againſt the</hi> King, <hi>and</hi> Kingly Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <hi>to which they ſay</hi> (Quakers Plea, <hi>p.</hi> 4.) Though ſome that are now called <hi>Quakers</hi> were once in the Army under the Powers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King, when their Knowledge and Judgments were not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe framed, but were of that Principle and Practice <hi>that Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and going to War in it ſelf, was lawful,</hi> &amp;c. yet being now altered, and turned in their Judgments to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, and that it is not lawful (in the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel) to fight againſt, or go to War with <hi>Carnal Weapons</hi> in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48969:10"/>any wiſe; there is now no danger of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> and now <hi>[We]</hi> are all of that Mind and Heart, that—it is on all <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions</hi> whatſoever un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to go to <hi>War</hi> and <hi>Fight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This pretended change of</hi> Judgment <hi>in G. Fox and his</hi> Preachers, <hi>is not to be taken for a change of their</hi> Judgment, <hi>for they ſay,</hi> it neither is, nor ever was in our Hearts ſince we own'd the Truth of God <hi>[to take up Arms</hi>] <hi>which is a Contradiction to their gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving directions and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to the</hi> Protector, Officers, <hi>and</hi> Souldiers <hi>concerning</hi> Fighting, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting them thereunto, and to go forth as an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in their</hi> Spirit; <hi>and blamed them for putting honeſt ſober Men, and thoſe that trembled at the Word of God out of the Army, and adviſing them to take ſuch in again. For <hi>G. F.</hi> and his</hi> Preachers <hi>can no more change their Judgments than the</hi> Pope <hi>can change his <hi>Decrees</hi> without forfeiting his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That they formerly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted Men to fight, and would fight themſelves, and now deny all Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on any pretence, is to be imputed to their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing and Deceit. For in the Book, entituled,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48969:11"/>Counſeland Advice,</hi> &amp;c. p. 44. <hi>
                     <hi>G. F.</hi> and <hi>E. B.</hi> tell <hi>Richard</hi>
                  </hi> Protector, That if he would walk with the Lord, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his People (<hi>mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Quakers,</hi>
                  </hi>) then <hi>(ſay they)</hi> Thy Name ſhall be greater than was thy Father's, and the numberleſs number of this (now) diſtreſſed People will be unto thee a Strength, and ſtand by thee in the day of trouble, and <hi>defend thee</hi> and thy <hi>Juſt Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and their Hearts ſnall cleave to thee, and thou ſhalt proſper for their ſakes, and none of thy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies ſhall have Power over thee to deſtroy thee. <hi>And in</hi> p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>they ſay,</hi> Friend, live in God's Wiſdom, if thou wilt reign in his Power and Strength, then none ſhall touch thee, and all them that fear God will be on thy ſide, and take thy part, and be one with thee in all thy Sufferings, yea, till death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſee how the eaſe was altered in</hi> 1662. <hi>for then they tell the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Parliament <hi>thus,</hi> And our Allegiance to the <hi>King,</hi> our Lives have, and ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to him, and you, and all Men. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by <hi>G. For, E.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48969:11"/>Burrough, F. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil, S. Fiſher, R. Hub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berthorn, G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, S. Thornton, L. Fell,</hi> and</hi> 20 <hi>more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And notwithſtanding that no People declared themſelves more fully for the</hi> Long Parliament Protectors, <hi>and</hi> Army <hi>than they, on condition they would own and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the <hi>Quakers;</hi> yet how ſhamefully do they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect on others, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim their own Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>See their Paper to the King and Council <hi>1660. p. 5.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH King! we would have thee do nothing againſt thy Proſperity and Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Oh! hath the like ever been done as is done to us, (who are an <hi>Innocent People, and thy Friends,</hi> and not thy Enemies) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the Princes in Chriſtendom to mingle the Innocent among the Tranſgreſſors! <hi>Again,</hi> p 6. Oh that we ſhould find ſuch things among you that have been Sufferers by the <hi>Same,</hi> as we have ſuffered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you.</p>
               <p>Obſ. <hi>What Hypocriſie is here, when they pretend that themſelves ſuffered for Righteouſneſs, and the King and his Party for wickedneſs and Tyranny?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48969:12"/>With like Deceit they ſay in their Declaration gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the King,</hi> Jan. 1660. <hi>ſubſcribed by twelve of their Grandees,</hi> p. 6. In the days of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Committee of Safety, we were looked upon as Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to bring in <hi>King Charles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <hi>So G. Fox</hi> and <hi>I. Stubs</hi> in <hi>G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads</hi> Book,</hi> The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, <hi>&amp;c. tell the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>and</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents, <hi>that</hi> when the People of God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers,</hi> were gathered together in divers places to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, then <hi>(ſay they)</hi> you ſaid they were Plotting together againſt <hi>Oliver,</hi> to bring in King <hi>Charles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Again,</hi> Touching Fighting, <hi>they have taken care to record what one of their Miniſtry ſaith,</hi>— We directed all People to the Spirit of the Lord God in them—and if that led them to fight, I had nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, <hi>fol.</hi> 4. <hi>[Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in their Book of Outland Letters, and was ſpoken before a Court at</hi> Barbadoes, <hi>where he was queſtioned touching their Principle in that caſe.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But in their Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the King,</hi> 1660. <hi>They ſay,</hi> p. 2. We cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48969:12"/>know, and ſo teſtifie to the World, that the Spirit of Chriſt which leads us into all <hi>Truth,</hi> will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver move us to ſight and war againſt any Man with Outward Weapons, neither for the Kingdom of Chriſt, nor for the Kingdoms of this World.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the former Paſſage they ſuppoſe the</hi> Spirit <hi>of the Lord might lead to fight; here they are po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive that it never will. And in their <hi>Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Magiſtrates,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſubſcribed by <hi>G. For</hi> and</hi> 11 <hi>more. They ſay all</hi> Plots, Conſpiracies, Alders, Aſſiſters, <hi>or</hi> Conſpirers <hi>thereunto, againſt the</hi> King, we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways did, and do ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny to be any of us. [<hi>And preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Execution of that worthy Patriot, the Lord</hi> Ruſſel, <hi>they preſent their fawning Addreſs (which</hi> G. Whitehead, Francis Camfield, <hi>and</hi> Gilbert Layty <hi>carried to</hi> Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor) <hi>to K.</hi> Charles 2. <hi>Inſinuating that the Lord</hi> R. <hi>and his Companions were</hi> Guilty <hi>and they</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, <hi>and that they did not</hi> deſire <hi>the leaſt hurt either to the King's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Government, or to the Perſon of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Duke of</hi> York, <hi>and that they were clear
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48969:13"/>from all <hi>Helliſh Plots</hi> and <hi>Trayterous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. <hi>being Works of the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But what's the reaſon the <hi>Quakers</hi> do not now declare againſt the late <hi>Helliſh Conſpiracy</hi> &amp;c. ſeeing one of the chief of them is accuſed of it by open Proclamation?</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And in their Paper to King and Council,</hi> p. 7. <hi>they ſay,</hi> We are againſt Violence and Plots, and Wars, and Fightings, they are below in the Fall from God. And this we ſay, which is more to us than an Oath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>See now what Credit is to be given to <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Miniſters in their moſt ſolemn Profeſſions, ſuch as Oaths are amongſt conſciencious honeſt Men! For it is well known that many Officers and Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers turning</hi> Quakers <hi>whilſt in Arms, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſo till they were thruſt out; and they that put them out are much blamed by <hi>G. F.</hi> and <hi>E. Burrough,</hi> &amp;c. for ſo doing, and are adviſed to take ſuch in again. Theſe are the Men that adviſe the</hi> Protector <hi>(as we have noted)</hi> to puſh down and tread under the High Places of Idolatry in all the Apoſtatized Churches, <hi>not only</hi> Papiſts, <hi>but</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:48969:13"/>others. <hi>And in another place,</hi> To cry up Chriſt the only King and Lord. <hi>Yet in their</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance <hi>p.</hi> 14. 665. <hi>They ſay,</hi> We our ſelves know that <hi>Sion</hi> muſt not be builded with Blood, nor the Church of God by Weapons of War, nor Religion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated by Violence, therefore we cannot ſtrive with theſe Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons nor with any Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Weapons of War, either fight to <hi>defend</hi> or <hi>offend.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let the Reader judge now whether <hi>G. F. G. W.</hi> and their <hi>Party,</hi> their reproaching, and railing on the</hi> Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians <hi>and</hi> Independents, <hi>and other Parties for their joyning and abetting the late War, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving the Execution done upon the late King and his Party, crying up <hi>Oliver</hi> and <hi>Richard,</hi> and the <hi>Old Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the Army,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and then when the King came in, changing their Language, crying up this King,</hi> &amp;c, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I ſay, <hi>G. F G. W.</hi> and their Party, are not far more guilty, and more abominable in theſe Matters than any other Party whatſoever, whilſt they ſo contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly upbraid others, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48969:14"/>have done the ſame things; and yet now under all theſe</hi> Contradictions, Diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, <hi>and</hi> Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing, <hi>do like the Whore in the</hi> Proverbs, <hi>wipe their Mouth, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim themſelves an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and harmleſs Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and others alone guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>See their Book, entitled, <hi>The Guide Miſtaken, 1668.</hi> p. <hi>50, 51, 52.</hi> They write thus,</head>
               <p>AT the beginning of the Wars <hi>[Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan Clapham]</hi> a moſt preciſe Stickler for a <hi>
                     <hi>Reformation.</hi>— But when the</hi> Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents <hi>were poſſeſſed of the Authority,</hi> — 'twas then the Beheaded King <hi>was by this Guide both Preached and Printed</hi> as a Toe of the Image, the little Stone, cut out of the Mountain without hands, was to ſmite; <hi>and therefore ſays,</hi> The Fall of the ten Kingdoms was begun; the Lord is riſen out of his Habitation, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay not; for who ſeeth not the Alteration is of the Lord. <hi>In another place ſays he,</hi> There can be no clearer Evidence that God is about this work of breaking own this great <hi>Image,</hi> and ſmiting the very Feet and Toes thereof,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48969:14"/>than this preſent Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over the <hi>Scottiſh Forces</hi> at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> (which we are now to render Thanksgiving to God for,) the Cauſe of this War being whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this <hi>Image</hi> ſhall be upheld, or the Feet, and the Toes broken. In ſhort, O ye honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Worthies whom the Lord hath raiſed up to effect theſe great Changes, carry on the Lord's Work, that your People may not have cauſe to ſay, we have changed our Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, not our Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.—<hi>'Twas alſo then in a Dedicatory Epiſtle to <hi>O. Cromwel,</hi> allowed by him of <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> Protector, <hi>to whom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst other extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Complements, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not let paſs theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, where he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites him,</hi> as God's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legate in Honour to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and out of the love to the Churches of Chriſt, for whoſe welfare, you have this Power com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to you;—<hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding</hi> thus, The Lord of Heaven and Earth bleſs your Highneſs with the continuance of his Gracious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with you, that as you have done valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the High Places
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48969:15"/>of the Field, <hi>(that is fought againſt the King and Biſhops)</hi> ſo you Go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vern as righteouſly and happily in the Gates of the City.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oh groſs Diſſimulation! Now 'tis he turns Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement Man, and is imployed by the ſeveral Churches in</hi> Norfolk <hi>to <hi>Richard Cromwel</hi> on the Death of <hi>Oliver,</hi> as their Repreſentative a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the</hi> Petition <hi>or</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs <hi>made by the Prieſts in general, which term the Father,</hi> Moſes, <hi>and the Son, the</hi> Joſhua, <hi>that ſhould Conduct them to the</hi> Holy-Land:—<hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the King came in, This</hi> Guide — <hi>changes <hi>Oliver, Richard,</hi> or <hi>Parliment,</hi> for <hi>Charles</hi>
                  </hi> (once a TOE of the Image that the little Stone was to ſmite) <hi>of</hi> England, Scotland, Ire<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land, <hi>&amp;c.—The Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed King</hi> (once the firſt broken Toe of the Image) <hi>now he Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morates with an Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary Sermon,</hi> &amp;c. — <hi>What temporizing is this? Oh what unheard of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie is here! But</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>What is thy Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Matter? Can</hi> Oliver <hi>be</hi> Moſes, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard <hi>be</hi> Joſhua, <hi>and</hi> Charles Defender of the Faith <hi>all together,</hi> p 53. Reader, <hi>Will this</hi> Fig-leaf-Garment
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48969:15"/>
                  <hi>cover the Shame of this</hi> Guide's <hi>Nackedneſs from thy Diſcerning and Cenſure, I hope not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>[Obſ. <hi>If the Epiſcopal Party had done this, would not the Quakers have call'd it a breach of the Act of Indemnity, and diſingenuous? But for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to do it who had as much need of an Act of Pardon as others, What was it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Again in their Anſwer to <hi>John Faldo,</hi>
                  </hi> Quakeriſm a new Nick-name, p. 109.</p>
               <p>And why, poor <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts,</hi> after all their Preacht up <hi>Batels, ſpoils, Plunders, Sacriledges, Derimations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Again</hi> p 119. Theſe are true Goſpel Miniſters whoſe Goſpel is Peace on Earth and good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Men, and not Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments rolled in the <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> no <hi>worldly Armies, Battels, Victories, Trophies, Spoils, Sequeſtrations, Decimations, and the like Blood-thirſty and Tyrannical Projects</hi> in which <hi>John Faldo</hi> and his poor <hi>Nonconforming Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> have had their Hands almoſt over Head and Ears, till they had well nigh loſt their Ears and their Heads too.</p>
               <p>[Obſ. <hi>Was not this to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and render obnoxious to the Government, and that in a time when the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt Miniſters were under Perſecution? Should any have expoſed the</hi> Quakers <hi>at ſuch a ſeaſon, What would they not
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48969:16"/>have ſaid couching the treacherouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and baſeneſs of it? And it ſeems this Mr.</hi> Faldo <hi>whom they thus vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie, was too young to be concerned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thoſe Projects. But what might he now ſay of ſome</hi> Quakers <hi>in relation to the preſent Government?</hi>]</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>See alſo their Book, entituled, <hi>A Juſt Rebuke to xxi Divines.</hi> p. <hi>25.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOw did the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>excite the Parliament in theſe very. Terms!</hi> Eliah oppoſed Idolatry and Oppreſſion, ſo do ye; down with <hi>Baal's</hi> Prieſts: <hi>which is as much as to ſay, Away with your Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops, the whole Miniſtry and Worſhip of the Church of</hi> England. <hi>Again,</hi> The Mouths of your Adverſaries are opened a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, that ſo many Delinquents <hi>(that is to ſay Royalists)</hi> are in Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and yet but very few of them brought to their Tryal, <hi>(did he mean to releaſe them.) And ſaith another of your Eminent Brethren before the Commons,</hi> Aug 28. 1644. Ye cannot Preach nor Pray them down immediately—well, that which the Word cannot do, the Sword ſhall.</p>
               <p>[Obſ. <hi>Again, Is not here expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and rendring of Perſons as ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the then Government as they could?</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This following is a Copy of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I writ to</hi> G. W. 22. February 1678. <hi>being above a Year after the fore-going was ſent them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>G. Whitehead, <hi>I have lately ſeen your Book, entitled,</hi> The Way caſt up <hi>&amp;c. and therein theſe following Paſſages,</hi> viz.</head>
               <p>ANd how many Garments were rolled in <hi>Blood</hi> by Inſtigation of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Teachers, the whole Nation was a Witneſs; ſo that many thouſands were made Widows and Fatherleſs by that War they ſtirred up the People unto, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p 23.</p>
               <p>[Obſ. <hi>Was not this that War, in which the</hi> Quakers <hi>ſaid the Army were Glorious Inſtruments in the Hand of God, and that God by his Spirit and Power was not only the</hi> Beginner <hi>but the</hi> Carryer on <hi>of that work, and that it was his preſence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48969:16"/>and power in the Army that gave them perfect Victory? And abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance more to the ſame purpoſe. Obſerve the other Column.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 52. Some of the <hi>Presbyterian Nonconformiſt Preachers</hi> are fled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, others lurk in Corners here and there, and keep private Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles; where many times they preach Sedition againſt their Lawful Prince; by inſtigation of whom, that Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection hapned in 1666.</p>
               <p>[Obſ. <hi>Could any thing more be ſaid by the Common Informers, or by the moſt inveterate Enemies of ſeparate. Meetings, than theſe Men here ſay and publiſh againſt the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians? Is not this a high degree of Malice againſt them, and Flattery of their Perſecutors?</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 53. And ſome of them have Printen Books in defence of the Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of making War againſt the Supreme Magiſtrate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[Obſ. <hi>And have not the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>Printed Books to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, particularly</hi> F. H. <hi>and</hi> E. B. To the Committees of Safety. <hi>See the other Column,</hi> p. 12, 13].</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>P.</hi> 54. And in very Truth, the <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Church</hi> will never be able to purge her ſelf of the Iniquity of killing many thouſands in the three Nations, by the occaſion of a moſt bloody War raiſed up through the Inſtigation of the <hi>Presbyterian, Teachers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>[Obſ. <hi>If the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>be thus guilty of ſheding of the Blood that was ſhed in that War, who diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the</hi> CAUSE <hi>before the King's Head was cut off, then what are the</hi> Quakers; <hi>who not only approved of what was then done, but incited the Army not to leave Root nor Branch of Idolatry, Oppreſſion, and Tyranny, till they had ſet up their Standard at the Gates of</hi> Rome, <hi>and to</hi> avenge <hi>the Blood of the Guiltleſs, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the Dominions of the Pope; which had the Army obeyed, would there not have been many more Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments rolled in the Blood of Kings, and People, than ever was in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? <hi>Let the Impartial Judge.</hi>]</p>
               <p>A Paragraph is omitted here for want of room.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:48969:17"/>
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding this Book was Printing, and the two Letters of my Name tranſpoſed, [which are now placedright,] I writ the following Paper, and ordered it to be inſerted here. <hi>J. P.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OH Earth, Earth, Earth, hearken and conſider! Was there ever ſuch a People as <hi>G. F. [G. W.]</hi> and their <hi>Party</hi> that had ſuch Foreheads and Faces of <hi>Braſs?</hi> who for about 20 Years have been reviling and recriminating others, for thoſe very things they have moſt highly been guilty of themſelves; yea, and were greatly offended with thoſe that would not go on further with the <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Cauſe</hi> they were then ingaged in, and did not only inſtigate and preſs <hi>Dliver, Richard,</hi> and the <hi>Army,</hi> to <hi>Crumble Nations to duſt,</hi> and to <hi>
                     <hi>Trample Deceit and Tyrants under,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> but alſo exhorted them not to leave off till they ſet their <hi>Standard</hi> on Top of <hi>Rome Gates,</hi> as is before mentioned; and yet upon the King's coming in, how did they ſeek to clear themſelves by accuſing others, as in the little Colum; and in another Book of theirs (lately come to my hands) entitled, <hi>Truth's Character of Profeſſors,</hi> they laid open the <hi>Addreſſes</hi> and <hi>Applications</hi> which others had made to <hi>D. C.</hi> and <hi>R. C.</hi> making long Animadverſions thereupon, not only to defame, but alſo to ſtir up the Powers againſt them, as in p. 15. <hi>viz. Muſt the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons that they have been forming againſt others be turned into their own Bowels!—even by ſuch as will have no more pitty in their Hearts towards them, than they have had towards the Innocent. And what! muſt not Jealouſie be ſtirred up in the Powers of the Earth againſt them, as they have ſtirred up Jealouſie in the Powers of the Earth againſt others,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And as they have ſought to make others ridiculous, even ſo ſhall they become contemptible in the Eyes of thoſe which they by their Flatteries fawned upon, who may for a ſeaſon ſuffer them for their own Ends,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But this was not all that was deſigned by <hi>
                     <hi>G. F.</hi> [and his Miniſters]</hi> ſo early defaming, crying out, and ſtirring up the Powers againſt other Profeſſors, but alſo to blind thoſe then in Power, as if themſelves had been altogether Innocent and clear touching thoſe Matters.</p>
               <p>And is it not ſtrange that they ſhould call the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in the late times, <hi>Rebels</hi> and <hi>Traytors</hi> for but endeavouring the King's Reſtauration; and yet after he was come in, moſt bitterly and invectively writ againſt them for being once Oppoſers of him. Are not theſe the Perſons that ſay, <hi>Their giving forth Papers or printed Books, it is from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Eternal Spirit of God? and that if ever we own the Prophets, Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, we muſt own their Writings, which are given forth by the ſame Spirit and Power: [And that they have thouſands at their Meetings, that none of them dare ſpeak a Word, but by eternal Motion:</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">A True Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, p. 18.</note>] And their ſo ſpeaking [i.e. <hi>Speaking by the Spirit</hi>] <hi>G. W.</hi> ſaith, <hi>is of as great Authority as the Scriptures and Chapters are, and</hi> Greater. Ser. Apol. <hi>p.</hi> 49.</p>
               <p>What ſhall we ſay to theſe Men! I am even ſtruck with Amazement, Aſtoniſhment, and Silence, that a People pretending ſo high, ſhould bring forth ſuch wicked and ungodly Fruits: and though ſome may be troubled that theſe are now come to light; yet others will not a little wonder that they have been hid and kept ſecret ſo long: And doubtleſs, <hi>had they not ſtill gone on inſinuating by Flatteries with the Government, and writing ſo reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly upon</hi> Diſſenters, <hi>with their Reproaching and Scandalizing other Sober Perſons more</hi> [Chaſt] <hi>and Innocent than themſelves;</hi> Theſe things had never come thus publick, and ſo they reap the Fruit of their own Doings, <hi>and that very way they thought to ſecure and ſtrengthen themſelves, hath helped forward their own Deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeeing there is no hopes of their Repentance or Forbearance, [<hi>as to theſe things</hi>]
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48969:17"/>(all other ways and means (which have not been a few that have been uſed to prevent them) proving ineffectual,) it is now thought meet thus to expoſe them [<hi>this year</hi> 91.] (as they for many Years have expoſed others,) that ſo if poſſible their Mouths and Pens may be ſtopt from any ſuch Procedure hereafter; and it may be, when too late, they'll remember, <hi>'Twas the Fooliſh and Clamorous Woman that pulled down her Houſe [which is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a pace] with her own Hands.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Here followeth one of the Forms of their <hi>Oaths,</hi> which <hi>Stephen Criſy,</hi> one of their great Preachers, impoſed upon one called a <hi>Quaker,</hi> who had Mortgag'd his Land to him and others for a Sum of Money; but before he would let him have the ſaid Money (notwithſtanding he had Signed and Sealed and Delivered according to their Agreement) he forced him (though with much diſſatisfaction) to Sign and Seal this following; (which by their own Definition of an <hi>Oath,</hi> is an abſolute <hi>Oath.</hi> Their Definition of an <hi>Oath</hi> is ſet down hereafter.)</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE—day—month—: I—do teſtifie in the truth of my Heart by theſe preſents; that whereas I have Mortgag'd an Eſtate of mine, lying in—in the County— unto</hi> Stephen Criſp <hi>Iunior,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>as by Deeds and Writings this day bearing date doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; I ſay, I do hereby teſtifie in the truth of my Heart, and in the Preſence of</hi> HIM <hi>that knoweth all things, and in the preſence of theſe faithful Witneſſes, that I have not before this Contract aforeſaid, contracted, bargain'd, ſold, or engag'd the ſaid Eſtate to, or with any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, either directly or indirectly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but that it was freely and abſolutely, both before, and at the Sealing and Delivery of the ſaid Mort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage above-mentioned, in my power to ſell,</hi> &amp;c.—</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Witneſs at Signing and Sealing, <hi>Samuel Newton, John Bolton,</hi> (two of their Preachers.)</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Now ſee their Definition of an <hi>Oath</hi> in their Anſwer to one <hi>J. S.</hi> who aſſerted that to ſay, God is my Witneſs. I ſay the Truth in Chriſt, I lye not, my Conſcience bearing me Witneſs in the Holy Ghoſt. I call God to Record on my Soul. The God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt knows that I lye not. And that <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Laban</hi> are ſaid to Swear in theſe Form of Words, So God is Witneſs between me and thee, were Oaths.</head>
               <p>[Obſ. <hi>Any of which, without laying the Hand on the Book, or other Ceremony, or more ſaying, is not only an <hi>Oath;</hi> but if Authorized by Act of Parliament, is as much a <hi>Legal Dath,</hi> as any now in uſe amongſt us.</hi>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>THE Quakers Anſwer</hi> to J.S. Theſe Forms of Speeches uſed by the Apoſtle, and by <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Laban, <hi>So God is Witueſs between me and thee. God is my Witneſs,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. are of themſelves (without the Addition of ſomewhat more as an outward Sign or Pledge) neither Oath or Swearing; which ſomewhat more, as an outward Sign or Pledge, was that which gave the Denomination of an Oath or Swearing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Again, That the Forms of Speech uſed by <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Laban,</hi> and by the Apoſtles and others—of themſelves, without adding of ſomewhat more as an outward Sign or Pledge, are neither Oaths or Swearing. It is worthy Obſervation, that where mention is made of an Oath or Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Scriptures of Truth, there is alſo mention made of ſome outward Sign or Pledge which was added to the Forms of Speech by them uſed; which ſomewhat more being added, was that which gave the Denomination of an Oath or Swearing to the Forms of Speech; without which addition of ſomewhat more than <hi>Yea</hi> or <hi>Nay,</hi> as a Sign or Pledge, the Forms of Speech of themſelves, was neither Legal Oath or Swearing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A ſecond Teſtimony concerning <hi>Oaths,</hi>
                  </hi> p. 3, 4, 5.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:48969:18"/>
               <head>A Copy of a Letter and Paper (mention'd in the <hi>Title-page</hi>) ſent to <hi>G. F.</hi> March 17. 1674/5.</head>
               <p>I Being ingaged (as well as ſome others) to manifeſt and lay open <hi>Deceitful Workers</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites;</hi> I am farther to appear and manifeſt thee to be one of the greateſt Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites and Deceivers in this Nation, and until thou own thy Condemnation, and leave off deceiving the People; aſſuredly, the <hi>Sword</hi> that's now drawn is not to be, nor muſt not be ſheath'd till thou and ſuch <hi>Deceivers</hi> as thou art be cut down. This following I am to ſend thee; concerning which I ſhall wait ſome time for thy Anſwer before it go far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and what thou writeſt to or concerning me; ſet thy own hand to it, and get not others to ſet their Names to thy words and works of Wickedneſs as thou haſt done.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="analysis">
            <head>Something of <hi>G. F's</hi> Deceit and Hypocriſie diſcovered.</head>
            <p>'TIS not unknown what great Deſires and Longings there was in the generality of the People of this Nation (in the Year 1659.) to have a King, by whom they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to be freed from thoſe Impoſitions they were under; but ſome others fearing if it were ſo, it would be for the worſe, cauſed a zeal in ſome particular Perſons to write againſt <hi>Kingly-Government;</hi> amongſt the reſt we find <hi>G. Fox,</hi> who (did not only write his own judgment barely as a Man (as others did,) but as a Man of GOD, taking upon him to inſtruct all others,) put forth a Book the ſame year 59. entitled, <hi>Several Papers given forth by</hi> G.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>But is this to render him Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to the</hi> Government; <hi>no I abhor that Practice, but baſe and ſelf-ended Spirits are to be humbled, and not think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves fit to cry down other Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Religion that have by</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery Perſecution <hi>and</hi> Falſeneſs <hi>too much reproached all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as ſaith</hi> Judas <hi>and the</hi> Jews; <hi>i.e.</hi> G. F. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> F. wherein he writes about ten pages againſt a <hi>King,</hi> and therein tells the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>There was no <hi>King</hi> owned among the true Chriſtians, but only amongſt the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, ſince Chriſt's time;—That they were <hi>Traytors</hi> to Chriſt that deſired a <hi>King;</hi>
               </hi>—and farther tells them what a <hi>King</hi> would be to them, (if they had one,) repeating thoſe words <hi>Samuel</hi> ſpake to the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi>—Then he bids them look what work <hi>Joſhua</hi> made with the <hi>Kings</hi> that were in the Cave <hi>(a fit place for them)</hi> ſays <hi>
                  <hi>G. Fox,</hi> p.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>But no ſooner the <hi>Scene</hi> of Affairs changed, but he changes his Dialect, and the very next Month after the King came in, he (with ſome others) put forth a Declaration, and therein they writ, <hi>That they owned and honoured the King and the preſent Government;</hi>—yea, they had flatteringly writ therein, <hi>That they were his Loyal Subjects, and that they had ſuffered much, as himſelf had done,</hi> &amp;c. And being called before a Court (in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi>) where the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> was tendred him, he told them, <hi>that if he could take any Oath in any caſe, he could take that Oath;</hi> and farther ſaid, <hi>he honoured all Men, much more the King,</hi> &amp;c. What! Is this the Man that ſaid <hi>They were <hi>Traytors</hi> to Christ that deſired a King?</hi> &amp;c. and now himſelf ſays, <hi>he honours all Men much more the King,</hi> &amp;c. Oh Strange! Is this he that is ſo highly eſteemed and exalted by his <hi>Proſelites,</hi> and even adored by ſome of his
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſi. Cole. Sol. Eccles,</hi> &amp;c.</note> Preachers, who ſtile him, <hi>The Father of many Nations.</hi> That <hi>Generations to come ſhall call him Bleſſed. Whoſe Being and Habitation is in the Power of the Higheſt. At whoſe Name the Heathen tremble, (or were pricked at the Heart
<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>A True Account,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 42.</note>.) The Bleſſed Man that came out of the North. Who hath been faithful in the Lord's Buſineſs from the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. That true Prophet, whom</hi> John <hi>ſaid he was not.</hi> And many more ſuch like Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, as, <hi>Innocent, Good, Holy, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright Man of God. Prophet indeed,</hi> &amp;c. Well, but what doth he ſay of himſelf? <hi>viz. That he is beyond the State of the Firſt</hi> Adam <hi>that fell;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48969:18"/>in the State of the Second</hi> Adam <hi>that never fell; yea, that his very Marriage was above the State of the First</hi> Adam <hi>in his</hi> Innocency, <hi>in the State of the Second</hi> Adam <hi>that never fell;—and that he never fell nor changed.</hi> And yet how hath he turned about with the Wind? which he ſaith <hi>they that are in the Fall do, and are in the changing changeable ways,</hi> &amp;c. And by his thus turning, and changing, doth it not manifeſt him to be in the Fall, Fallen, and changeable State, according to his own Words? And yet how far is he from the leaſt acknowledment thereof, that he goes on and ſays, <hi>He hath power to bind and to looſe whom he pleaſes?</hi> And takes upon him to make <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Orders</hi> for People, and appoints them <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> when and where to Worſhip; yea, this is he that preſumed to alter (or cauſed to be altered) [<hi>unto which</hi> G. Whitehead <hi>was Privy</hi>] the very ſubſtance of a Paper that was declared to be writ from the Spirit of GOD; and ſo adulterated, ſends it beyond Sea, which <hi>John Oſgood, William Penington</hi> and my ſelf complained of to ſome of the Chief Preachers, but not one of them would (or through fear durſt) ſay that he had done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs therein, notwithſtanding the <hi>Forgery</hi> was ſo manifeſt; and the Author ſaid (when he came to ſee it) that he was abuſed in it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this coming lately to publick view, is ſtill ſo far from being diſown'd or condemn'd; that <hi>Judas, &amp;c.</hi> endeavours to cover and juſtifie it with this Saying, <hi>The Spirit of the Prophets muſt be ſubject to the Prophets.</hi> Oh horrid Impudence and Wickedneſs! not only to commit ſo great an Iniquity, but to bring the Holy Man's words to Patronize and Juſtifie ſuch an <hi>Enormous Fact.</hi> Certainly none that truly fears GOD, who ſhall come to the knowledge of theſe things, will either own him to be a Servant or Prophet of the LORD, until he come to Repentance for theſe and other his Wickedneſſes; among the reſt, that of getting Perſons to ſet their Names to his abuſive Papers and Writings, and alſo that of his villifying, reproaching, and bely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe that oppoſe him, (how vertuous and innocent ſoever they be:) Can any paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel him herein?) with his (and his Adherents) late fawning, flattering Addreſs to the King and Parliament; wherein are theſe words; <hi>And the Oaths provided to testifie Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the King, and denial of the Pope's Supremacy in Cauſes Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, the Refuſal whereof incurs a Premunire; has been executed upon ſuch whoſe</hi> Hearts <hi>and</hi> Hands <hi>could ſeal to the Subſtance thereof.—And yet their Conſciences not allowing them to Swear at all (becauſe of the Command of Chriſt;) for that Only they have been the ſole Sufferers thereby.</hi>— And (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Cloſe) they ſay, <hi>That if they be called to bear witneſs, or any Office, to or for she King, or their Country, and teſtifie their Truth or Faithfulneſs, to one or both, in which Caſes Oaths are uſually required and impoſed. They deſire and requeſt that an Act or Proviſion might be made, That their Yea, and Nay, may be accepted and taken inſtead thereof,</hi> &amp;c. Concerning which I ſhall ſay little more at preſent, but conclude with a few words formerly writ by another [<hi>concerning them</hi>] <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>What will you do? You <hi>Scribes, Phariſees, Hypocrites,</hi> you that have been long making clean the outſide of the Cup and Platter, but inwardly are as <hi>Ravening Wolves,</hi> your Fruits will make you manifeſt; you <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> your Name will be a ſtink among the Heathen for the LORD will find you out, whoſe Glory He will not give to any other, nor His Honour to any of your Graven Images: My Soul loaths all your falſe Covers; ye <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> I cannot but declare againſt all your falſe ways.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Days of <hi>Viſitation</hi> are come, the Days of <hi>Recompenſe</hi> are come,</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall know it, I will recompenſe them according to the Works of their own Hands: They have ſown the</hi> Wind, <hi>and they ſhall reap the</hi> WHIRLWIND.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_preachers">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:48969:19"/>
            <head>For the <hi>Preachers</hi> and <hi>Leaders</hi> of the People, called, QUAKERS.</head>
            <p>YOUR Day into <hi>Darkneſs</hi> is turned; the Sun is gone down over you: You have had a large Day and Power given you, to have done the Will of GOD; but you have abuſed the Power, and ſlighted your Day, and have refuſed to do the LORD's Work, and have ſought your Selves, and not the LORD; therefore in Juſtice and Righteouſneſs is the Day, wherein you might have wrought for GOD, taken from you, and the thick <hi>Dark Night</hi> of Confuſion is come upon you, wherein you are groping, and ſtumbling, and cannot work: The <hi>DECREE</hi> is gone out, and it cannot be recalled. You are not the Men (as ye ſtand) in whom GOD will appear to work Deliverance for His People, (and yet Deliverance ſhall come;) but as for You, ye have rejected the Counſel of the LORD, and grieved His Spirit, and He hath long born you; yea, You are departed from the LORD, and His Preſence is departed from You: Indeed He hath <hi>hewed</hi> with You, (and if you had been faithful to the End, He would have <hi>honoured</hi> and <hi>proſpered</hi> You, and have been your ſufficient Reward:) Ye were His <hi>AX,</hi> but you have boaſted your ſelves againſt Him: Therefore as you have <hi>hewed</hi> and <hi>broken</hi> others, even ſo muſt You be <hi>hewed</hi> and <hi>broken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O ye <hi>Treacherous, Wilful, Proud, Self-ſeeking</hi> People! who have deſpiſed the Counſel of the LORD, and would not take warning, though He hath ſent His Servants among you, <hi>ſome</hi> of whom you have deſpitefully uſed; What will ye do now? Whom will you now flee unto for help? Seeing you are departed from the LORD. Remember your End, which haſtens greatly; <hi>Breach</hi> upon <hi>Breach, Diviſion</hi> upon <hi>Diviſion</hi> ſhall there be, until HE come to Reign whoſe Right it is.</p>
            <p>They that truſt in, or lean upon You for help, it is as if they leaned upon a <hi>broken Reed,</hi> which is not able to help it ſelf nor others. You have been made to do many good things, but you would not go through with the Work which GOD will have accompliſh'd, and therefore are theſe things come upon you. Therefore <hi>tremble</hi> and <hi>dread</hi> before the LORD, Ye who have been as ſtrong Oaks, and tall Cedars; for now ſhall your Strength fail you, and you ſhall be weak, even as the weakeſt of Men: But if you would yet ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to GOD's righteous Judgments, you might come to witneſs your Souls ſaved in the DAY of the LORD; though many are to be thrown by (becauſe of grievous Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlidings) as not counted worthy to be the LORD's Workmen.</p>
            <p>There is a ſmall Remnant yet among you (for whom my Soul breaths) who may be Winnowed out; and if they will own the Judgments of the LORD, and truly and throughly deny themſelves, and ſollow His Leadings, He will heal their Backſlidings; but they that will continue with you in your <hi>Sins,</hi> ſhall partake with you of your <hi>Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The foregoing Words (excepting the Title) were writ (by another)</hi> 1659. <hi>to the then</hi> Rulers, <hi>upon whom they were fulfilled; and ſo as certainly ſhall they be fulfilled upon you.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>[<hi>This was Printed, and given them in</hi> April 1673. <hi>much of which being already fulfill'd, and believing the remainder will, in its appointed ſeaſon; cauſeth me to have it reprinted and placed here, that whoever reads and conſiders it (as alſo what</hi> W. R. F. B. T. C. W. M. <hi>and others have written concerning them) may plainly ſee they have been warned of their great</hi> Apoſtacy <hi>and</hi> Downfal <hi>many years agoe.</hi>]</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48969:19"/>
            <head>SOME REMARKS Upon a Book, entitled, <hi>Chriſt's Lambs defended againſt Satan's rage,</hi> &amp;c. Being the <hi>Quakers</hi> Anſwer to <hi>The Quakers Vnmask'd,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>In a Letter to</hi> E. S. <abbr>
                  <hi>Eſq</hi>
               </abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving had the curioſity and opportunity of reading, <hi>
                  <hi>The Quakers Vnmask'd,</hi> Their Double dealing and Falſe-heartedneſs diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,</hi> &amp;c. I thought it impoſſible for the <hi>Quakers</hi> to vindicate themſelves from that Authors Charge; which made me deſirous to read their Anſwer; and having peruſed it, I can ſcarce forbear to Remark ſome few Paſſages, which are clear Confutations of their boaſted <hi>Innocency, Plainneſs, and Chriſtian Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Advertiſement to the Reader, <hi>G. Whitehead</hi> takes notice that <hi>The Quakers Vnmask'd,</hi> &amp;c. was ſent them in Manuſcript in the year 1677. and that Liberty of Conſcience being eſtabliſhed by Law, and placed upon the Book in writing, is the cauſe of its now publication. <hi>Which</hi> (ſays <hi>G. W.) looks as if he envyed our preſent Liberty.</hi> Behold the Spirit of this Anſwerer! Mr. <hi>Pennyman</hi> kept his Books unpub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed for 13 years together, leſt it might be any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Perſecution; but when Liberty of Conſcience is eſtabliſhed by Law, he publiſheth 10 or 11 of them, preſuming there is now no danger of their being perſecuted. Does this look as if he envyed their preſent Liberty, and not rather that he was glad of it, as no doubt he is.</p>
            <p>In p. 6. to the Reader. <q>Our Adverſary, again p 14. <hi>(ſays he)</hi> deals very unfairly and unjuſtly by <hi>G. W.</hi> about ſome of our Friends, ſaying, They give forth Writings from the immediate Eternal Spirit of God, and by the ſame Spirit and Power that was in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles; unto which he falſly addeth, And their ſo ſpeaking (G. W. <hi>ſaith</hi>) is of as great Authority as the Scriptures and Chapters are, and greater; his words (and their ſo ſpeaking) are <hi>J. P</hi>'s own Abuſe and Perverſion.</q> Now I beſeech you, Sir, read the Paſſage in p. 14. and ſee wherein <hi>J. P</hi>'s Abuſe and Perverſion lies. It lies in this, that he added theſe words [<hi>and their ſo ſpeaking</hi>] and did not put them in a different Character, to diſtinguiſh them from <hi>G. W's</hi> words, though they did not alter the ſenſe at all; if you leave them out, the Paſſage is as much to the ſame purpoſe, as if they were in. Did ever any Writer charge his Adverſary with Abuſe and Perverſion upon ſo ſlender an account? What an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front is it to the ſimple-hearted Reader to write at this rate? This is the Man that in his Letter to <hi>J. O.</hi> threatens Mr. <hi>P. farther to detect and unmask him if he will not be reduced to Chriſtianity.</hi> Does he mean by Chriſtianity, <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> which it ſeems teaches him to uſe the baſeſt Equivocations and Slights that can be found in any Writer?</p>
            <p>Of his Book, p. 3. <hi>He utterly denies it as a Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the</hi> Quakers <hi>formerly exhorted Men to fight and would fight themſelves.</hi> I muſt refer you to <hi>The Quakers Vnmask'd,</hi> &amp;c. to judge whether that is a Slander, or not? It will abundantly ſatisfie you, whilſt you underſtand their Writings in the plain ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſenſe of the Words without their after Equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations. <hi>J. P</hi> cites one of the, <hi>Quakers</hi> Miniſters, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>We directed all People to the Spirit of God in them, and if that led them to fight, I had nothing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it;</hi> for this, ſaith <hi>G. W.</hi> he quotes, fol. 4. but tells us not what Book. But why did he not tell <hi>J. P</hi> ſo 13 years ago when he deſired to know what Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors they ſound in the Quotations, (if there were any; however to ſatisfie him that it was a true citation, he took it out of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Book, where Foreign Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were recorded, which was firſt in <hi>J. O</hi>'s cuſtody and afterwards in <hi>J. P</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 4. The <hi>Quakers</hi> tell <hi>Rich.</hi> Protector, 'That he would walk with the Lord, and preſerve his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, then thy Name ſhall be greater than was the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48969:20"/>Fathers, and the numberleſs number of this [Now] diſtreſſed People will be unto thee a ſtrength, and ſtand by thee, and <hi>Defend thee and thy juſt Government.</hi> Sir, If you had been Protector, I perſuade my ſelf, you would have thought theſe People would have fought to defend you and your Government: But whatever they or you thought then, the meaning now is, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> they would defend him and his Government, <hi>By Righteouſneſs, Prayers, and Faith, and by Contributions, Taxes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or the fear of the Lord,</hi> as in the days of <hi>Jehoſaphat.</hi> Would you not judge that Man perjured, that ſhould ſwear Allegiance in ſuch terms, with ſuch a meaning? And muſt we not take the <hi>Quakers</hi> words for as binding as an Oath?</p>
            <p>Next, <hi>p.</hi> 5. you will pleaſe to note what <hi>G.W.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to the Charge of <hi>upbraiding others with that which themſelves, for many years, were as deeply concerned and ingaged in,</hi> &amp;c. <q>To all which, ſaith <hi>G. W.</hi> I do conſcientiouſly Anſwer, He hath moſt groſly and palpably belyed the People cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers</hi> in theſe Paſſages divers ways. Firſt, in rendring them, without exception of Perſons, not only Juſtifiers of the late Wars, and what had been done therein, without exception of things done, but alſo equally concerned with the <hi>Presbyterians, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,</hi> and others therein.</q> But do the <hi>Quakers</hi> when they charge theſe things upon the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> &amp;c. make any exception of Perſons or Things? And yet it is well known, and it is proved out of their own writings in <hi>The Quakers Vnmask'd,</hi> &amp;c. that their Chief Leaders approved of the greateſt things done in the late Wars againſt the King, and to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; whereas the Presbyterians generally diſ-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of them. Beſides they ſay, <hi>their giving forth Papers or Printed Books, is from the immediate eternal Spirit of God,</hi> and that <hi>their Preachers are guided by an Infallible Spirit, and that they are of one Mind and Judgment,</hi> and the like; and therefore an indefinite, and general charge will affect them more generally than other Parties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays, p. 6. <q>The War began in 41. and in 48 the King was Beheaded, and all this while no <hi>Quakers</hi> heard of, till about 50.51, 52. when there was no Wars in <hi>England</hi> for them to be concerned in, how falſe then is <hi>J P.</hi> to ſay, The <hi>Quakers</hi> were as much, or more, concerned in the War againſt the King as any others.</q> But <hi>G. W.</hi> confeſſes, that <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers who have been ſince, and now of us,</hi> [Quakers,] <hi>have formerly been concerned in the late Wars.</hi> And <hi>J. P.</hi> has made evident their approbation of what was then done, and that many that turned <hi>Quakers</hi> in the Armies, continued there till they were turned out, that the Protector is blamed for putting them out by G. <hi>Fox</hi> and others, that they are called, <hi>Sober Men and true Hearts that feared God and trembled at His Word, valiant Captains, Soldiers, and Officers, it may be for ſaying thou to a ſingle Perſon, or for wearing their Hats,</hi> &amp;c. the diſtinguiſhing Characters of <hi>Quakers</hi> from others. Whereas, he ſays, there was no Wars in <hi>England</hi> in 50.51.52. it is a piece of his cunning, and is falſe; for <hi>Worceſter</hi> Fight was in the year 51. and Sir <hi>George Booth</hi>'s Inſurrection in 1659. when the <hi>Quakers</hi> gave intelligence, calling them Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, for but endeavouring to bring in the King; and for ſome years there were Wars both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and upon the Sea, and in <hi>Flanders.</hi> See <hi>E. Burrough</hi>'s <hi>Alarm Sounded,</hi> &amp;c. 1659. <hi>The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Vnmask'd,</hi> &amp;c. p. 6. 9. You ſee then how <hi>G. W</hi>'s Anſwer is both falſe and deceitful</p>
            <p>P. 7. 8. <hi>G. VV.</hi> charges <hi>J. P.</hi> with an apparent lye, in ſaying, the <hi>Quakers</hi> had been engaged in the ſame Cauſe, ſo as <hi>to Preach up Battels,</hi> &amp;c. But I pray Sir, what difference is there between Preaching up Battles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and exhorting Generals, Officers, and Soldiers, to go forth againſt mighty Enemies till they had ſubdued them, and ſet up their Standard a top of <hi>Rome,</hi> and done many other things which were to be done by Fighting? And that in the <hi>Quakers</hi> Spirit. See <hi>E. B's Alarm Sounded,</hi> &amp;c. p 28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P</hi> 9, 10. <hi>G.W.</hi> Commends the <hi>Quakers</hi> for their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance towards <hi>J. P. and is confident that had</hi> J. P. <hi>look'd upon them as Fighters,</hi> &amp;c <hi>he durſt not have adventured to have given them ſuch frequent and publick occaſions of provocations and frequent diſturbances and interruptions.</hi> To this, <hi>J. P.</hi> ſaith, he hath always been careful never to interrupt them, nor to give them any diſturbance otherwiſe than by ſpeaking a few words, either before they began to Preach, or when any one of them had done Preaching; and though the words which he ſpoke they could not gainſay, but were true; yet becauſe they look'd upon t, that in what he ſpake he meant them therefore (notwithſtanding his peaceable behaviour) he has ſometimes found himſelf in much danger from the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> who have frequently done violence to him them ſelves, and that in the place where he has a Propriety.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 10. They would excuſe <hi>G. Fox</hi> in what he ſays againſt an <hi>Earthly King,</hi> &amp;c. by turning it into an <hi>Earthly oppreſſing King, and ſetting an Earthly King over them,</hi> p. 11. But did not King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond (to whom they addreſſed ſo early, profeſſing their Innocency formerly, and their preſent Truth and Fidelity to him) challenge the Supreme Power over the Church? <hi>Are not all theſe Elders Chriſtians, that will dote ſo much of an Earthly King</hi> Traytors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt? ſays <hi>G. Fox;</hi> And whom did they dote upon but <hi>Charles</hi> 2 (and afterwards upon King <hi>James</hi>) whom the <hi>Quakers</hi> do now <hi>love, own, and honour?</hi> Neither do you read, ſaith <hi>G. F. that there ever was an Earthly King ſince the days of the Apoſtles, but
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48969:20"/>amongſt the Apoſtate Chriſtians.</hi> So then according to their own Principle, when King <hi>Charles</hi> 2. was among the <hi>Quakers</hi> he was among Apoſtate Chriſtians; or elſe they temporiz'd and changed their Principles, holding that there might be an <hi>Earthly King</hi> among true Chriſtians. And how could they profeſs their Innocency to the King, and that none had any juſt cauſe againſt them, ſince they had maintained ſuch Principles as aforeſaid? The caſe of the Prophet <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> was far different from that of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> he was chief Magiſtrate himſelf, and they a little part of a People that had put to Death their King, and kept out the Heir by Arms, (of both which the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſufficiently approved.) Now, ſuppoſe, <hi>Samuel</hi> had been the Repreſentative of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the Heir made King contrary to his mind and endeavour, would he have addreſſed him, and ſaid. <q>You are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, O King, with my Principle and Practice, neither have known my Innocency and Sufferings, they that ſpeak againſt me as a Perſon that was an Oppoſer of your Kingſhip, and did vehemently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort the People from ſubjecting themſelves to your Arbitrary and Oppreſſive Power, had no juſt ground for that Charge. I love, own, and honour you and your Government.</q> Might not the King have an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd him, Are not you aſham'd, <hi>Samuel,</hi> to play the Hypocrite in this groſs manner? Do you brag of <hi>your Principle, and Practice, and Innocency</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me in this matter, ſince if the People had acted according to your Principle, and done as you would have had them, I ſhould never have recovered my Kingdoms? If you are innocent, who is guilty? Is this your Innocent Plainneſs? Who then is Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Deceitful? Your Pride will not ſuffer you to acknowledge any Error in Principle or Practice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye have profeſs'd to ſpeak and write from the immediate Eternal Spirit of GOD, though you are found fallible and fooliſh as other Men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 15. <hi>The Quakers Vnmask'd,</hi> is cited, ſaying, <hi>Are not they in their own Judgments become Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, for now they ſay we love, own, and honour an Earthly King. G. W.</hi> anſwers, p. 16. <hi>And where do we uſe theſe very words</hi> Earthly King <hi>on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but that we love, own, and honour the King, (whom here this Mau has judged an Earthly King,) does this ſhew us to be Apoſtates. Remark</hi> Did you ever read a more frivolous Anſwer? Was it any other King but that very King <hi>Charles</hi> 2. whom they had writ ſo bitterly againſt, under the Name of an <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly King?</hi> he was an <hi>Earthly King</hi> before, when they ſaid, <hi>They were Traytors againſt Chriſt that will dote ſo much on an Earthly King;</hi> but now the <hi>Quakers</hi> love, own, and honour him, he ſhall not be called an <hi>Earthly King.</hi> He was an <hi>Earthly King</hi> before when the <hi>Epiſcopals</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> doted on him; but now he is become the <hi>Quakers</hi> King he muſt be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what elſe; I preſume not a Heavenly King; but this is ſomewhat of the <hi>Quakers</hi> plainneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 19. <hi>G.W.</hi> ſays, <q>I am perſuaded that reproving him [<hi>O. C.</hi> Protector] for putting ſuch [as feared GOD, ſober Men and true Hearts, becauſe of their faithfulneſs to the LORD,] out of the Army for their Conſciences, was MORE upon his breach of Promiſe, than with an intent to have them always continue in it, in order to War and Fight.</q> Here <hi>G. W.</hi> or whoever writ this paſſage, would ſeem to have ſome ſenſe of Conſcience; for his ſaying MORE is a comparative with what follows; and argues that it was written with an intent to have had them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to continue in the Army in order to War and Fight, <hi>though MORE upon his breach of Promiſe.</hi> I doubt we ſhall not find <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> guilty of ſo much openneſs again throughout the whole Book. Do not the <hi>Quakers</hi> hold that none fear GOD truly and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but themſelves? <hi>That they are in the Truth, and none but they; and only among them is GOD known?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt was not contradictory to himſelf in bidding his Diſciples to ſell their Garments, and buy Swords, and conſequently to wear Swords (as <hi>Peter</hi> did,) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe He ſaith my Kingdom is not of this World, or from hence; but Chriſt was contradictory to the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſenſe of that ſaying, becauſe if it was not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Fight, in any caſe, Chriſt would never have bid them buy Swords: But I did not intend to argue the lawfulneſs of Fighting, only <hi>G. W.</hi> brings it in need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 21. One of their chiefeſt Preachers had ſaid, <hi>It is no Rebellion to call away thoſe in Power;</hi> by which <hi>J. P.</hi> underſtands to Depoſe <hi>thoſe in Power that perform not their Truſt: G. W.</hi> calls this a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe addition of a meaning, <hi>as if to</hi> call away <hi>and to</hi> Depoſe <hi>were both one in common acceptance.</hi> But <hi>G. W.</hi> is not pleaſed to tell us what other thing was meant by it, and I am perſuaded that no Man but a fore-warn'd <hi>Quaker</hi> will take them for other than both one.</p>
            <p>But I muſt haſten; read his 23 page, and you will find it amount to this, <hi>Had you</hi> [the Army] <hi>been faithful to the Power of the LORD GOD, you had gon into</hi> Spain <hi>to require the Blood of the Innocent, —and knock'd at</hi> Rome <hi>Gates,</hi> &amp;c. [And done wonderful great things by wicked and unchriſtian Fighting, or otherwiſe by the fear and terror of your Power, Arms, and Conqueſts without Fighting,] <hi>or as the Hoſt of the</hi> Midianites <hi>fled and were overcome.</hi> and yet not by Fighting <hi>on</hi> Gideon<hi>'s part, but by a mean Stratagem. Quere,</hi> Whether they that kill by Stratagem do not Fight? And when the <hi>Ephraimites</hi> ſlew <hi>Oreb</hi> and <hi>Zeeb,</hi> and brought their Heads to <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon,</hi> and purſued <hi>Midian,</hi> they did not Fight?
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48969:21"/>
               <hi>Judges.</hi> 7.25. And whether <hi>Barack, Jepthah, Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, David, Samuel,</hi> and the Prophets, who by Faith ſubdued Kingdoms, and turned to flight the Armies of the Aliens did not Fight? <hi>G.W.</hi> has found out all theſe ways of an Army's Conquering without Fighting. Sir, I know you are an impartial Man, can you think ſeriouſly (not that any Man to whom the <hi>Quakers</hi> wrote, or any Man that ſhould read what they wrote, would underſtand them in any ſuch ſenſe, without Fighting; for I take it for manifeſt no Man did; but) whether they that wrote, or even the <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves, (till now they are preſs'd with theſe paſſages,) ever thought of ſuch Senſes? And if not, where is the <hi>Quakers</hi> plainneſs, whereof they ſo nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouſly boaſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 24. <hi>G. W.</hi> ſays, <hi>It cannot conſiſt with our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Principle, ſo much as to avenge our ſelves.</hi> Who are more ready to avenge themſelves in Word and Print than <hi>Quakers?</hi> How have they railed and reviled their Oppoſers? Witneſs thoſe Names <hi>G. W.</hi> calls <hi>Will. Rogers, F. Bugg, Tho. Criſp</hi> and others, in the Preface to his Book, <hi>Judgment fixed,</hi> viz. <hi>Apoſtate-Informers, Treacherous Hypocrites, Falſe Brethren, and Deceitful Workers, Betraying Indas's, Devils Incarnate, who having toſt their firſt love to Truth, and gone out from us, are become degenerate, without Natural Affections, Dogs that are without, Wolves, and raging waves of the Sea, that foam out their own ſhame.</hi> And a multitude of other ſuch like Names do they call thoſe that oppoſe, and cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to their outward Preſcriptions and Impoſitions, beſides their frequent violence with their own Hands,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>See the complaint of one of their own People, touching this matter,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It hath been their lot to be haled, (with violence) out of the Aſſemblies,— Did I think to ſee the ſame violence offered in our Aſſemblies! Nay, but with Sorrow, mine Eyes have ſeen pulling down, haling out, and thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth of our Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and they went to the utmoſt, as far as their Power; and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they wanted not Will but Power to puniſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And although they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xerciſe the Oppreſſions before-mentioned,</hi> (and much more as may be ſeen in the ſaid Book;) <hi>yet by their deceitful flatterits, they make People believe, That they are <hi>harmleſs, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> and <hi>peaceable Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, ſuffering and bearing wrong but not doing any.</hi> And if any Perſon write, or ſpeak their Grief, they will repreſent them under ſuch terms as may render them odious; and the more effectually to weaken their Teſtimonies they will fix upon them ſcurrilous and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible Appellations, as <hi>Scotch-Men, Welch men, Tinker, Taylor,</hi>
                     </hi> &amp;c. <hi>Some of them utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true; and to prevent an Inquiſition into the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they would make People believe, that they are <hi>envious, malicious, and diſcompoſed Spirits, bad, dirty, factions, and ranting Spirits, who are gone from Truth, and are out of Truth.</hi> Such is the Portion of thoſe that appear in the leaſt againſt their imperious, tyrannical, and laſcivious Actions: And whatever Man detected the Falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and deſtructive Cheats of imperious, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful Men, but was thus reproached?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Muſt it be Juſtice in them to complain of their Oppreſſions; and Envy, and Malice,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>in us to complain of ours? Their years are but few; yet verily they have been exceeding expert to learn of the Papiſts, Subtilties.</hi> Spirit of the Hat, <hi>p.</hi> 29, 36, 37.</p>
               </note> and what is a great part of this Book of <hi>G W. &amp;c.</hi> but avenging themſelves of <hi>J. P.?</hi> They might have ſaid all they had to ſay in their own vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, without thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold reproaches, and even Curſes, which they belch out againſt him, ſuch as that in p. 30 <hi>God will ſmite thee, thou malicious Hypocrite. Our Innocency ſhall riſe up in Judgment againſt thee.</hi> Read to the end of that Paragraph. Of this nature is <hi>G. W.</hi> glorying, that <hi>Jer. Ives not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his malicious Works againſt us</hi> [Quakers] <hi>was ſoon cut off by Death,</hi> p. 33.</p>
            <p>I muſt deſire you, Sir, to read p. 34, 35, 36, 37. of their Vindication of that Declaration to which Mr. <hi>P</hi>—'s Name was amongſt the reſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and then judge what <hi>diſingenuity and deceit</hi> there was in him, to inſert the ſubſtance of that Declaration, without telling that his own Name was to it, ſince his Name was not to thoſe after Declarations, which are inconſiſtent with this. 2. Whether it is poſſible to give a more Equivocating An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to any charge, than <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> has given of this? They ſay, <hi>God might command Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands and Ten Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of His Saints, at this Day, to Fight in His own Cauſe</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>This paſſage, and the like, the</hi> Quakers <hi>left out in the reprint of</hi> E. B<hi>'s works, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (it ſeems) they would expoſe them in their clear ſenſe; but being brought to light, they then ſtudy to put an equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocal ſenſe on them.</hi>
               </note>. But <hi>it muſt not be taken for granted</hi> (ſays <hi>G. W.</hi>) <hi>that therefore he would do it.</hi> But that which GOD may do, and which <hi>we cannot yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that He will make uſe of us in that way,</hi> and therefore <hi>for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent we are given up to bear and ſuffer,</hi> &amp;c We muſt needs conclude that this is one of thoſe things that GOD hath made no DECREE to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but that He may Will it to be done, even by us in the future, though He hath not done it at preſent. And all that <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> has Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiz'd upon the Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocalneſs of the term YET, does but bewray his and their Equivoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for though YET may be taken for Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, when they ſay,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48969:21"/>but YET His Kingdom <hi>is not of this World;</hi> notwithſtanding it cannot be ſo taken, when they ſay, <hi>neither can we YET be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> &amp;c. but it muſt be taken to denote the time to this preſent <hi>[adhuc, as yet]</hi> in exception to the time to come; eſpecially when it is farther ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained by the clauſe, <hi>for the preſent;</hi> which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily oppoſed to the time to come, and imports clearly that Fighting may be commanded as in the Future, as now bearing and ſuffering is commanded. I am very confident that <hi>G. W. &amp;c.</hi> cannot produce any one inſtance out of any Man's Writings, that underſtood well the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue, of the uſe of the term <hi>Yet,</hi> in ſuch a Phraſe and Conſtruction, in any other ſenſe than of <hi>Time.</hi> But if all uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd Readers muſt and will underſtand it in this ſenſe, then <hi>G. W's</hi> Anſwer is full of groſs Equivo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the People that exalt themſelves above all other Profeſſors whatſoever, that they reckon all them to be of the World, out of the Truth; and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>the Only People of GOD, and that they are in the Truth, and none but they, Chriſt's Lambs,</hi> and the like. And for diſtinguiſhing themſelves from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they took up ſome Obſervances, or Ceremonies, which did it effectually; ſuch as ſaying <hi>Thou</hi> not <hi>You</hi> to a ſingle Perſon; calling no Man <hi>Maſter,</hi> but <hi>John</hi> or <hi>Thomas, &amp;c.</hi> not <hi>I thank you,</hi> but <hi>I receive thy love;</hi> not carrying the Feet but the Head foremoſt of their Dead, and the like. They condemn utterly the courteſie of putting off the Hat to any. In ſhort, they affected ſingularity in moſt things that were cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in <hi>England,</hi> how innocent ſoever: And under the notion of not Swearing, they only refuſe the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of an Oath, as the laying the Hand upon, and Kiſſing the Book. Now, I pray Sir, what of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, or real Goodneſs, is there in theſe things? Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the whole World did obſerve them, would they be at all the better for it? However, by theſe things they have cut off all others, how religious and ſincere ſoever. And if any Man oppoſe what they ſay or do, inſtead of meekly anſwering, they are ready with the moſt virulent, opprobrious, and threatning Language and Writings that can be found in any ſort whatever. They will diligently ſeek out, and take up any thing may reproach one; and will inſinuate Crimes that Men are moſt free from: Thus have they changed the Meekneſs and Gentleneſs of Chriſtianity, into Fierceneſs and Churliſhneſs; Humility and Modeſty, into Arrogance and Self-conceit; Peaceableneſs into Contentiouſneſs; Mildneſs into Clamour; and Bleſſing into evil ſpeaking and reviling; Plainneſs and Simpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, into-Equivocation and Craft; and all this under the Profeſſion of the moſt unſpotted Innocency and Sincerity. Truth, Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs.</p>
            <p>But I would not be underſtood to impute theſe Immoralities to the <hi>Quakers</hi> in general, nor to all their Teachers and Leading Men, but to the <hi>Foxonian</hi> Party that love to Govern and have the Preheminence, who have endeavoured to ſuppreſs thoſe who have at any time propoſed any thing contrary to their Sentiments. Thus in a few years, inſtead of being led and guided, and being obedient every one to the Light in himſelf, they were obliged to ſubmit to the ſenſe of the greater number of the Governing BODY, though never ſo contrary to their own ſenſe. Nay, this Impoſing Spirit proceeded ſo far, at a Quarterly Meeting in <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> where they did not act with that Caution and Cunning as here at <hi>London,</hi> that they made and ſubſcribed this following Order, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>I deſire to give up my whole Concern, if required, both <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> unto the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> in Men and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men's Meetings, as believing it to be more according to the Univerſal Wiſdom of <hi>God,</hi> than any particular meaſure in my ſelf, or any particulars with whom the Men and Women's Meetings have not Unity.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The Actings, Writings, and Speakings of that kind I have ſpoken of, being obſerved by ſome
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>W. Rogers, T. Criſp, F. Bugg, W. Macklow, J. Story, J. Wilkinſon, Charles Harris, J. Rance, Tho. Curtis, J. Anſloe,</hi> and many more.</note> among them, who were either too wiſe, or too honeſt to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, that thoſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Fruits could pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed either from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, or from the Light within, that they griev'd and mourn'd to ſee that excellent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Reformation, <hi>The Light in every Man,</hi> ſo groſly perverted and undermined, that they were made to oppoſe and teſtifie againſt them.</p>
            <p>Sir, I might go on throughout <hi>G. W.</hi>'s <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whole Book, and ſhew many more groſs Equivocations, Palliations, and Deceits; but I will not proceed far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, leſt I may ſeem to queſtion your Judgment, in not obſerving thoſe things that are ſo evident. But I think we that read Books have juſt cauſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt thoſe <hi>Quakers,</hi> who have the face to impoſe upon the World ſuch abominable Stuff, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Notion of the Teachings of the Light, of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48969:22"/>the unſpotted Innocency and Chriſtian ſincerity. But it may reaſonably be thought they write not for vindication of themſelves to thoſe that are of the World, (as they call all that are not in their Form;) but for their own Party, that are ſo blindly addicted to their Leaders, that they ſwallow every thing they ſay without conſideration: Unhappy Men! that have given up their Minds to the Glory of a ſingular Party, in contempt of all others, and can find no other way of vindicating themſelves. I may need your excuſe for writing ſo much, and therefore will now ſubſcribe</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute> 
               <signed> Yours A. C.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 23. 1691.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AND beſides what I ſaid about Fighting, I am credibly informed, that ſome <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> have not only fought, but that with great Courage and Magnanimity. The firſt I ſhall mention is Mr. <hi>William Mead</hi> an eminent Perſon, who being ſet upon by three High-way-men, and having only a Cudgel, or Staff, in his Hand, did not only bravely defend himſelf therewith, but knock'd down one of the Robbers ſo wounded, that the other were forced to carry him away, whilſt Mr. <hi>Mead</hi> eſcaped their Hands. The next ſhall be one <hi>Matthew Renſhaw</hi> (Maſter of a Ship,) who fought both with great and ſmall Guns, till he was overpowered by the <hi>Turks.</hi> Another, one <hi>John Thompſon,</hi> who fought exceeding ſtoutly, and killed a great many Men before he was taken by the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Theſe two Maſters were not only <hi>Quakers</hi> themſelves, but their Owners gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, if not every one, ſuch. More might be named, but theſe ſuffice to ſhew that the <hi>Quakers</hi> will fight in a juſt Cauſe, and that ſtoutly too; which puts me in mind again of <hi>G. Fox To the Council of Officers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 5. who ſays (of thoſe that had been put out of the Army for being <hi>Quakers,) Of whom it hath been ſaid among you, that they had rather have had one of them than</hi> 7 <hi>Men, and could have turned one of them to ſeven Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince my writing the above, I have ſpoken with Mr. <hi>Pennyman</hi> touching the Accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt <hi>Stephen Criſp,</hi> mentioned in <hi>The Quakers Unmask'd,</hi> folio p. 14. and which in their <hi>Anſwer,</hi> p. 14. they ſay, <hi>Steph. Criſp abſolutely denies, that he either forced him, or that the Party did ſhew any diſſatisfaction before he Signed and Sealed the ſaid Paper.</hi> Oh! what ſhall we ſay to theſe Men, who not only uſe Equivocatious in their Writings, but do abſolutely deny matter of Fact? to which Mr. <hi>Pennyman</hi> was an Eye and Ear-Witneſs, and is ready to atteſt it, if called thereto; but would not then ſubſcribe as a Witneſs, being greatly diſſatisfied with the unworthineſs of the demand.</p>
            <p>I will add here ſomething concerning the Nature of an Oath, whereby it may appear that the <hi>Quakers</hi> are miſtaken about it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="analysis">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:48969:22"/>
            <head>Of the Nature of an Oath.</head>
            <p>WHen the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſays (<hi>Ch.</hi> 6.16.) <hi>Men verily Swear by the greater; and an Oath for Confirmation is to them an end of all ſtrife;</hi> he plainly ſhews us, that an Oath is the greateſt and utmoſt Evidence of Truth and Sincerity that can be given; for if a Man openly appeals to GOD, who ſearcheth the Heart, and therefore knows not only what is outward in Men's Words and Actions, but their moſt inward thoughts, that Man gives the utmoſt aſſurance he can poſſibly give; for he that falſifies in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Men, calling them for Witneſſes, who know the matter, and whoſe office it is to ludge and puniſh, incurs all that reproach, infamy and other puniſhments, which ſo great an offence and abuſe deſerves: So he that falſifies in the preſence of God, calling Him for Witneſs, incurs the greateſt puniſhments of Divine Vengeance, as one that makes God Almighty a Partner and Confederate to a Lie, preſumptuouſly and to his very face. So that however God perhaps is not expreſly invocated to do vengeance upon him, yet in appealing to God as a Witneſs, that is implyed, becauſe He is ſuch a Witneſs as is alſo the Supreme Judge, whoſe Juſtice and Truth is herein appealed to. Therefore calling God to Witneſs is as much an Oath as any other form of Words, as having as much evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and aſſurance as any other Form whatever, and as great Penalties attending it. Now to aſſert any thing in the preſence of Men expreſly, is all one as to call them for Witneſſes: So alſo to aſſert any thing in the preſence of God expreſly, is all one as to call God for Witneſs.</p>
            <div type="oath">
               <head>Farther ſee ſeveral Forms of an Oath. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I <hi>Do hereby testifie in the Truth of my Heart, and in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of HIM that knoweth all things, and in the Preſence of theſe Faithful Witneſſes,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">The Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Form. <hi>p.</hi> 25.</note> &amp;c. Or, <hi>GOD is my Witneſs. I call GOD to record on my Soul. The GOD and Father of our LORD Jeſus Chriſt knows that I lye not. GOD is Witneſs between me and thee.</hi> Any of which (or the like) without laying the Hand on the Book, or other Ceremony, or more Words, is not only an Oath, but, [as ſaith a knowing, judicious, and worthy Perſon,] if Authorized by Act of Parliament, is as much a <hi>Legal Oath</hi> as any now in uſe amongſt us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="criticism">
               <p>And as the <hi>Quakers</hi> have been miſtaken about an Oath, ſo they have been about their paying of Taxes, in that they allow'd and paid the <hi>Royal Aid</hi> Tax, and that of carrying on the Waragainſt the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and the like; yet they would not pay towards the Trained Bands, notwithſtanding they are chiefly intended for a Defence; and the other, not only to Defend but to offend our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, as the Government ſees cauſe. So that 'tis plain, the Tax they then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed was more juſtifiable than that they allowed and paid, inaſmuch as to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend is more allowable and juſtifiable than to Offend.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
